<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The complaint of English subjects delivered in two parts. First part, is the complaint, of the poor, middle, and meanest sorts of subjects, concerning their bodily assistance. Second part, is the true Christians complaint, against vice, and wickedness, for the good of their soul's health. Also, werein is set forth, the late prodigious growth, of atheism, errors, and vice: with a call to repentance. As also, how needful it is, in these times, for every one of us, first of all, to look into our own hearts, and endeavour to amend what is their amiss. And lastly, a brief discourse, concerning our late unfruitful, and cold summers: as also, what is thought to be the real causes of it, by way of opposition, to the opinion of astrologers. By Richard Newnam of Tiverton in Devonshire.</title>
            <author>Newnam, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218651</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830224</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2035:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The complaint of English subjects delivered in two parts. First part, is the complaint, of the poor, middle, and meanest sorts of subjects, concerning their bodily assistance. Second part, is the true Christians complaint, against vice, and wickedness, for the good of their soul's health. Also, werein is set forth, the late prodigious growth, of atheism, errors, and vice: with a call to repentance. As also, how needful it is, in these times, for every one of us, first of all, to look into our own hearts, and endeavour to amend what is their amiss. And lastly, a brief discourse, concerning our late unfruitful, and cold summers: as also, what is thought to be the real causes of it, by way of opposition, to the opinion of astrologers. By Richard Newnam of Tiverton in Devonshire.</title>
                  <author>Newnam, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56, 49-111, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: The complaints of the poor, middle, and meanest sorts of English subjects, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Durham University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Social conditions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Social life and customs --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:1"/>
            <p>THE COMPLAINT OF Engliſh Subjects, Delivered in Two Parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> Is the Complaint, of the Poor, Middle, and Meaneſt ſorts of Subjects, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Bodily Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second Part,</hi> Is the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Complaint, againſt Vice, and Wickedneſs, for the good of their Soul's health.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Werein is ſet forth, the Late prodigious Growth, of <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, Errors,</hi> and <hi>Vice:</hi> With a Call to Repentance.</p>
            <p>As alſo, How needful it is, in theſe Times, for every one of us, firſt of all, to look into our own Hearts, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to amend what is their amiſs.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> A Brief Diſcourſe, concerning our Late Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful, and Cold Summers: As alſo, what is thought to be the real Cauſes of it, by way of Oppoſition, to the Opinion of <hi>Aſtrologers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Newnam</hi> of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 30.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There is a Generation, whoſe Teeth are as Swords, and their Jan-teeth as Knives, to devour the Poor from off the Earth, and the Needy from among Men.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 31.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Open thy Mouth, judge Righteouſly, and plead the Cauſe of the Poor, and the Needy.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 20.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Mercy and Truth, [preſerve] the King; and his Throne is upholden by Mercy.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 4.1, 2, 3. Eccleſ. 5.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <l>Come ſee, and Read, and ponder well, behold,</l>
            <l>Ile ſhew you Droſs, that's mixt with pure Gold;</l>
            <l>See that with care, this Gold, from droſs, you ſever,</l>
            <l>Do, as I ſay, and you (may) live for ever.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have here undertaken the doing of that, which was the Duty of ſome one, or other, that is much more Eminent, and better Learned, than I am: For mean was my Education, and Scholar I am none, farther than the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, and that I underſtand but Imperfectly. And therefore, through weakneſs I may err, in many of my Expreſſions, but (however) I hope the moſt Learned, and the moſt Ingenious, will have ſo much reſpect for me, as to deal with me, in the Examination of my following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, as the upright Judge doth, in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of Witneſſes, who regardeth (more) the Truth of their Evidences, than the manner of their Dialect, when ſpoken but with a home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Tongue: For Truth, is Truth ſtill, as well that which is ſpoken in a plain Dialect, and homely Speech, as that which is ſpoken in the moſt higheſt Rhetorick, (or) moſt ſweeteſt Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. It is only Plain Truth, and Naked Truth, that I now intend to ſpeak; and only
<pb facs="tcp:34674:3"/>ſuch Truth, as hath in it, true Honeſty, true Chriſtianity, and true Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Thus refering to your Judgments, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, theſe, and all other of theſe, my follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſes or Sayings, with all humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and true Devotion, ſubſcribe my ſelf, as really I am, obedient to my Superiours, truly Loyal to my King, and a Well-wiſher to my Country, whilſt I am Yours</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Richard Newnam.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:3"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">To His Moſt Gratious Majeſty, <hi>William</hi> the Third, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith; And alſo, to the moſt Honourable Parliament theſe I moſt humbly dedicate.</head>
            <p>AND now with all humble Submiſſion, ſay, what I have here done, I think is but my [Duty] ſo to do; for the ſtrict Ties (of the Oaths) of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, requires me (not to conceal) any thing that may prove detrimental to my King and Country. Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is much abuſed, the Country moſt grievouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, and oppreſt; their Trade is meerly loſt, and in their Eſtates and Minds they are much decayed; and this at laſt (muſt needs) be highly Detrimental, both to Your moſt Gratious Majeſty, and the moſt Honourable Parliament, and to all others, that are Your Majeſty's true Loyal Subjects. And therefore, however, ſo illy, or fooliſhly, I have either managed, or worded, this my following Treatiſe, yet nevertheleſs, I hope, Your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, will be pleaſed to accept of my Good-will, as theſe are intended by me, no otherwiſe, than for the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Honour and Safety, of Your most Gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; as alſo, for the general Good of all Your Majeſty's faithful Subjects, who I fear, are now much more liable to the malice of Enemies, than otherwiſe Your Royal Self,
<pb facs="tcp:34674:4"/>or they could ever have been, had not ſuch men, as I have herein deſcribed, done, from time to time, ſuch things, as they always have done, yet nevertheleſs, by the Power of the Almighty God, and Your Aſſiſtance, it is yet an eaſie matter, to amend what is amiſs, and thereby wholly put a ſtop to all the Deſigns of Your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which God by his infinite Power, with Your means, grant it to be done, is the earneſt Prayer of him, who is Your Majeſty's true Loyal Subject, and the Honourable Parliaments devoted Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RICHARD NEWNAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <p>AND now before I proceed on the main of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by way of <hi>Introduction,</hi> I ſhall give you a brief Account of the Heads of all my following Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> of all, herein is ſet forth the Great Abuſes, that of late hath been done, and ſtill is done, both to Your Majeſty and the Country, by means of the undue Execution, of Your Majeſty's and the late Parliaments ſeveral Acts, made for the raiſing of the ſeveral Sums of money, from time to time, on the ſeveral Lands and Stocks, of all Your Majeſty's Subjects within this our Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> The unſpeakable Loſſes and Damages, that of late hath, and still doth, lie on our whole Nation, by means of the most Wicked Actions of ſome men, who in the time of the Revolution of our late Coin, made even as it were a meer Prey, on all Your Majeſty's good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects, and thereby made themſelves extreamly Rich, and our Nation in general very Poor. And alſo, herein is ſet forth, by what means they accompliſhed their wicked Deſigns, as alſo, how they Truckt, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, Changed, Sold and Diſpoſed, the greateſt part of it, and where they lodged it at laſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:4"/>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> How all manner of Trading is decayed, and even as it were meerly come to nothing; and all this is moſtly occaſioned, in and by the means, of the ſeveral Loſſes and Damages, which all ſorts of honeſt Trades-men, of the middle and meaner ſorts of them, have received in and by the Revolution of the late Coin, which hath ever ſince put them to great ſtreights, through want of money, ſo as that by means thereof, they are now many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them, throughout <hi>England,</hi> for ever made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of a comfortable Living here on Earth, except ſome ſpeedy Courſe be taken for their Relief.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4thly,</hi> How ſorely and grievouſly the Taxes of <hi>Births,</hi> and <hi>Burials,</hi> do gaul and pinch, the poor and meaneſt ſorts of Your Majeſty's good Subjects. But on the contrary, herein is ſet forth, how deſirable a thing it is, for the Rich and great Ones of our Nation, to have the opportunity to pay Birth-Taxes: And alſo, for Death-Taxes, amongſt them, how then 'tis in their own power to make themſelves no loſers, by any ſuch Taxes, as ſhall at any time hereafter become due from they, or any of them.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5thly,</hi> What a most wicked Trade is now of late ſprung up, and uſed amongſt ſome Evil-minded men, who Buy and Sell all ſorts of Corn, in and by ſuch Clandeſtine ways and means, as that thereby, they will always create a Dearth, on all ſorts of Grain in the midst of the greateſt Plenty; and this to the Poor, is now a preſent Sorrow added to their former Affliction.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6thly,</hi> That notwithſtanding all thoſe hard and dear times, that of late hath been, and now is, yet all this doth not ſtop or turn the Hearts of our Mobb or Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond ſturdy Poor, who are now become more bold, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, prophane, and wicked, than ever yet before: Alſo, ſome Reaſons are ſhewed why they are ſo now, more than heretofore in times paſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:5"/>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7thly,</hi> How all my ſeveral Diſcourſes; are to my ſelf all known Truths, by true Information given me, and by experience tryed, and by way of Obſervation made on mens Actions, here with us in our County of <hi>Devon.</hi> Alſo, herein is ſet forth a ſhort Comment on our late and unfruitful Cold Summers, which we have had for ſome conſiderable time paſt, Year after Year; for which Cauſes ſome Aſtrologers, pretend to ſhew the true Reaſons of it: But by my ſelf, their Reaſons for that are denyed, and my own Reaſons in oppoſition to theirs, are in my follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſes inſerted.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8thly,</hi> I have contracted, the ſum of all my ſeveral Diſcourſes, in a few plain low ſtile <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſes, whoſe Sound and Dreſs, are eaſie, plain and ſimple: but without Compounds, of any Fraud, or Flattery; and ſo I moſt humbly offer them, hoping they may be rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, and juſtly applyed, as they are by me (Truly) Loyally, and Innocently, ſet forth for the Good of all Men, here in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Nation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34674:5"/>
            <head>The Complaints of the poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>And now may it Pleaſe Your Moſt Gratious Majeſty, and the Honourable Parliament:</head>
               <p>THeſe had been long ſince preſented unto your Greatneſs, had I not been from time to time continually prevented, by being much Exerciſed with many Troubles, which of late Years I have labour'd hard under them; which Troubles were brought on me, partly through the means of theſe our late hard times, as alſo by a mixture of ſome other Calamities, which the Hand of Providence was pleas'd to caſt upon me. And tho' I have good reaſon to complain, as to my own particular part, yet 'tis not my own Cauſe, that I take on me now to vindicate; but the Cauſes of many others, whoſe conditions are far more deplorable than mine. But however, as my ſelf am a great Sufferer, therefore I cannot otherwiſe but commiſerate the conditions of ſuch, as are far greater Sufferers than I now am: But ſhould this long continue, then 'tis much to be doubted, that at laſt, we may be all Sufferers alike; for the prevention of which I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon me, after much delay of time, to offer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34674:6"/>you theſe, which had been more fit to have been preſented long ago. But beſides theſe my troubles, before mentioned, I muſt ingeniouſly confeſs, that I have delayed the doing of it moſtly, becauſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, until now, I had always on my Spirit a continual awe and dread, which made me caſt up within my Breaſt many doubts, fearing leſt through weakneſs, or ignorance, I ſhould herein offend ſo great Authority, as I acknowledge Your moſt Gracious Majeſty and the Parliament are: For when I conſidered with my ſelf on the greatneſs of your Power and Wiſdom, as alſo, on my own mean condition, and weak capacity, it did always make me dread the thoughts of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. And thus under this great fear, I have delayed much time; and yet, I could never avoid my having much Contemplation about it; for many and often have been the times, that I have controverted in my own thoughts on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, and Unconveniencies of this Work, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till at laſt I came to this Reſolve; firſt with my Heart and Tongue, to commit my works unto God; and next, with my Hands and Pen, I would offer them to the Judgments of Men: And I was encouraged ſo to do; after I had well conſidered that ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> in Chapter 16 of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> verſ. 3. 'tis there ſaid, <hi>Commit thy Works unto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall be eſtabliſhed.</hi> In hopes of which I further ſay;</p>
               <p>Great Sirs, think it not ſtrange, that ſo mean a Perſon as I am, ſhould take upon me to write unto you in this way and manner; for no Man can do any thing but by permiſſion, or inſtigation; It is God that permitteth me, and the Spirit of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34674:6"/>Truth that juſtifieth me to ſay, That if ever there were a time to ſpeak in due ſeaſon for <hi>England</hi>'s Good, I think now is the time; And it may be high time, yet hope not paſt time. Tho' great may be the Troubles of our Land, becauſe great are the Sins of our Nation, and moſt grievous are the Burthens that do now lie on the poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of Your Majeſty's faithful and true loyal Subjects, by means of ſome unworthy Men, I mean ſome of the late and now preſent Aſſeſſors and Commiſſioners, who have abuſed that moſt noble and honourable Truſt put in them, and confer'd upon them by Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty, and the late Parliament; and inſtead of performing that Truſt, by a juſt and due Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Your Juſt Laws, they have even as it were by meer Violence, oppreſſed Your middle and meaneſt ſorts of Subjects; and inſtead of doing Juſtice to all Men, have eaſed themſelves, and have laid the Burthen on ſuch as could not, nor cannot bear it, to the utter Ruin of many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands throughout <hi>England:</hi> And alſo, have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by leſſen'd Your Majeſty's Revenues from time to to time, I believe, at leaſt, ſome Millions of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, which might have been juſtly riſen to Your Majeſty's uſe, barely and only on the ſeveral Taxes of <hi>Four Shillings</hi> and <hi>Three Shillings</hi> the <hi>Pound</hi> on Lands and Stocks, if the Rich had but from time to time paid proportionably to their Abilities, as they always have from time to time compelled Your Majeſty's poor, middle, and meaner ſorts of Subjects to do.</p>
               <p>And I do aver it for a Truth, that in the <hi>Town</hi> of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> ſuch Matter s as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34674:7"/>ſaid, were, and always are, ſo unjuſtly carried: And there are many Men in that Place, that then were, and now are, worth ſome Thouſands of Pounds in their Stocks, particularly each Man of them; and yet then were, and now are rated but for Two hundred Pound Stock each particular Man. And alſo, there are in our ſaid Town of <hi>Tiverton</hi> aforeſaid, ſome Men, that then were, and now are worth in ſtock <hi>Ten thouſand Pound</hi> each Man; And ſome that are reported to be worth in Stock <hi>twenty thouſand pound</hi> each man, and yet were not, nor are not rated for more than a <hi>few hundred pounds</hi> Stock each man, of the Richeſt ſort of them, as I am credibly informed. And alſo, in their Lands, all of them were ſo undervalued, as that they were, and now are Rated no higher for them, proportionably, then they were rated for their Stocks; And yet, at the ſame time, they Rated the ſeveral parcels of the Lands and Tenements of Your Majeſty's middle, and meaner ſort of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to the full height and value of all, or moſt of them. And this ſore and grievous Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is not only uſed and ſtill practiſed in <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> but as far as I can underſtand, is continually uſed and practiſed all <hi>England</hi> over: and ſuch Evil Doings can never be well-pleaſing in the Eyes of God, or in the ſight of good Men; for to do Juſtly, and to love Mercy, is but our Duty, with humble ſubmiſſion, in obedience to the Laws of God. And it is the duty of every Man ſo to do, according to that eſtate or degree which he is plac'd in, here in this World; the truth of which is verified by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Micha,</hi> as you may read it in Chap. 6. verſ. 8.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34674:7"/>He there ſaith, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do Juſtly, and to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.</hi> And alſo, agreeable to this is that moſt excellent Command of our moſt great Lord and Maſter, our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as we may read it in the 7th Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, verſ. 12. theſe his own Words, <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> And thus from Chriſt's own Words, we may ſee that the doing of Juſtice to our Neighbour, and upright dealing between Man and Man, is highly neceſſary towards every man's Salvation.</p>
               <p>But here a Query doth neceſſarily ariſe; and the poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's true Loyal Subjects may ſay, <hi>Have thoſe Men, whom we complain against, done by us as they would be done unto, had their Cauſe been ours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay No: and conſequently I ſay again, they have not ſhewed themſelves like true Chriſtians, nor can I think ſuch Men to be true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or true Loyal Subjects: And tho' they have ſaid, and do ſay, that they will hazard their Lives and all that they are worth, for the ſake of Your Majeſty, and the Proteſtant Religion; yet I can not believe them: for can any Man ſerve God and Mammon all at one time? or can ſuch Men be true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that will do ſuch vild and abominable things, which the very <hi>Heathens</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor? or can ſuch Men be truly Loyal to the King, when at the ſame time they do as it were meerly rob him of his juſt Revenues. And then by their unjuſt dealings, to ſave their own Caſh, do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34674:8"/>even as it were meerly undermine Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty, (out of the love of many) of your middle, and meaner ſorts of Subjects, who otherwiſe in Your Defence, and by Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Command, and the moſt Honourable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments aſſiſtance, would bravely Branniſh the Sword over the Heads of all Your Enemies, and ſtoutly fight the Battel in and for Your Majeſty's defence, if any farther occaſion ſhould be for it, as already they have done; for were not Your Majeſty's Armies of late moſtly filled up by and with Your middle, and meaner ſorts of Subjects? And was it not they that ſtood the violent Shocks of Your Majeſty's Enemies? And again they will ſtand it for you, except in the mean time too much Poverty make them weak handed, or unwilling. And if their be not a ſpeedy ſtop put to the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of ſuch Actions, as I have here mentioned, then 'tis much to be feared that an Enemy in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time may take advantage of it; and then, if occaſion ſhould be for it, to ſerve Your again, Your Majeſty may find too many of Your poor, middle, and meaner ſorts of true Loyal Subjects, feeble-hearted, and weak-handed, and not capable to do Your Majeſty that ſervice, which otherwiſe they would do You.</p>
               <p>And thus I have, in ſome meaſure, truly and plainly, diſcovered to Your Greatneſs, <hi>England</hi>'s preſent Malady: But the Remedy, with all numble ſubmiſſion, I leave to the great Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings and Care of Your Moſt Gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the preſent Parliament: And now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently cannot otherwiſe but ſay as followeth.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34674:8"/>
               <q>
                  <l>He that ſpeaks plain, hath in his Heart no guile,</l>
                  <l>But he's moſt falſe, that hates when he doth ſmile:</l>
                  <l>Some ſuch perfidious Souls on Earth there be,</l>
                  <l>But ſuch a Soul ſhall not be found in me.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>[Prov. 14.25, 28, 34. Prov. 20.28.]</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>But, <hi>Secondly;</hi> There are ſeveral other Great, and Grievous Crimes, and other Wicked Actions, that of late were, and now are continually commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, done, and ſuffered to be done amongſt us, ſome of them are too notoriouſly known, and yet go unpuniſhed; and others of them not ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known, and therefore ſuch Offenders think themſelves out of all danger of puniſhment: But however, it may be neceſſary to lay open all theſe Crimes and Actions to more publick view, than yet perhaps they have been known; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be (in ſome meaſure) a means to abate their courage, and to ſtop them from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on in a full Carere of other Wickedneſs, which ſuch Men will be always doing in and by, ſome way or other. Beſides, it is ſome ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the loſer, to know where his Goods are, and who the Thief is, altho' it be paſt all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of having them again, yet if ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, after they are known, can be brought to condigne puniſhment, according to their ſeveral deſerts, then 'twill be for the better. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to ſet forth all their Actions in perfect Colours, as they really are, I am at a loſs, for my capacity cannot fathom the bottom of them; I ſhall want Words to expreſs them, or if by my capacity I could paint them out to the Life, yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34674:9"/>I think it not convenient to do it now, becauſe I want both time and room: For my deſign now is to offer to Your Majeſty and the Parliament but a few Sheets; but if I ſhould undertake to ſet forth all thoſe ſeveral Crimes, and other wicked Actions in particulars, then I muſt make this my Work ſwell to a conſiderable Volume.</p>
               <p>And now finding that 'twill be too tedious to perſiſt on all the particulars of ſuch Crimes, and other wicked Actions, therefore I will moſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed on, and endeavour to ſet forth the generals of ſuch horrid Crimes, and other wicked Actions, as aforeſaid. And the firſt Crime that I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet forth, ſhall be the moſt horrid Frauds, Cheats, and Perjuries, that too many of our Nation were guilty of, in the time of the Revolution of our late Coin: And alſo, ſhall endeavour to ſet forth the manner and way, how they acted their Frauds, Cheats, and Perjuries, and the ſeveral ways and means they then took for the accompliſhing of them; as alſo, where they lodged all their Frauds, Cheats, and Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at laſt.</p>
               <p>And now for the better Explanation of it, firſt of all, Metaphorically I ſay; This deviliſh Trade had its firſt Riſe and Growth from Clippers, and Falſe Coiners of Money, who laid their Heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and conſulted how they might have a trade: And then immediately up ſtarted a ſubtile Fellow amongſt them, and ſaid, <q>Gentlemen, the People ſay that no manner of crack'd Money will paſs any longer: But if you will be rul'd by me, we will make it all paſs one way or other.</q> But then ſays another of the Company,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34674:9"/>
                  <q>How can we make all manner of crackt Money paſs, for ſome is crack'd almoſt through; and ſuch crack'd Money as that cannot be made to paſs.</q> But then again ſays that cunning ſubtile Fellow that firſt ſtarted the Queſtion; <q>Pray Sir, hear me; Doth not all manner of Clipt Money paſs without any objection made againſt it, tho' never ſo ſmall? And there is a great deal of good broad Money that is but a little crack'd, and ſome of it not quite to the Ring: and what if it be crack'd home to the Ring, all ſuch Money we can Clip, and afterwards it will paſs currently: And then all ſuch Money as is deeply crack'd, we can melt down, and new Coin it and Clip it afterwards.</q> But then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently up ſtarted an expert falſe Coiner, and ſaid, <q>What need we give our ſelves double trouble? Why, do ye think that a piece of Money is not to be new made, in imitation of old clipt Money?</q> 
                  <q>No, Sir, (ſays the Clipper)</q> 
                  <q>I beg your Pardon, (ſays the Falſe Coiner) He's a bad Artiſt to his Trade that can't do that.</q> Then reply'd ſome other of the Clippers; <q>I believe, Sir, you your ſelf cannot do it.</q> Then the Falſe Coiner reply'd again, <q>Sirs, I will warrant to do it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially and compleatly; and in the doing of it, I will not uſe ſix penny-worth of Silver in a Shilling, and but little more than nine penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth in Half a Crown, and yet he ſhall be a good Artiſt that diſcovers it; and if it do look ſomewhat courſer in the Eye of an Artiſt, the Country will not take notice of it: But on the whole, at ſuch a rate as I have told you, I will make all ſuch Money paſſable, without obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</q>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34674:10"/>
                  <q>Nay, (ſaid the whole Company) if you can do ſo, our Buſineſs is done.</q> Then ſays that Falſe Coiner, <q>Gentlemen, reſt your ſelves contented in this matter; by me you ſhall ſee it done, and therefore let's now talk no more about it. Come, drink about, for our Trade will now and than afford us a Glaſs of Sack.</q> 
                  <q>Ay, (ſays another of the company) and a Rope to boot for ſome of us, if we have not the more care on't.</q> 
                  <q>Tuſh, (ſays another of the ſame Company) we muſt all venture that.</q> And ſo with a merry Fit of Laughter amongſt them, they all caſt off the thoughts of Hanging for it: And thus they all agreed. And then by their Maker, they all ſwore Fidelity to one another; and then (ſhaking each other by the Hand) they all una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly promiſed each other, never to diſcover one the other, if any of them were taken in the Fact. And ſo unanimouſly they went on with their Trade, ſome to Clipping, and ſome to Falſe Coining; the latter of which 'tis ſuppoſed there was abundance of it made, and in a littie time, ſuch ſorts of Money became very plenty, and it was ſcattered all <hi>England</hi> over in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; and for a ſhort time it procured a very quick, brisk and vigorous Trade: But note, Trading was then encouraged, only to put off this ſmall Money, which was then the only cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent running Money in our Nation. And it is ſuppoſed by ſome, that for the love of putting off ſuch ſorts of ſmall Money, brought Guinnea's to ſo high a Price; for there came down here into the Country pretended Merchants, and gathered up all the Guinea's that they could get, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34674:10"/>changed ſuch Small Monies for them: And alſo, 'twas ſaid, that then at that time, there were many Men with Seventy Pounds of Broad Money each particular Man, bought One Hundred Pounds of this then Small current Money, which yielded the then Buyers the full value of One Hundred Pound of Lawful Money of <hi>England:</hi> And thus thoſe Money-Buyers were at that rate ſupplyed, as often as they then had occaſion for it. And was not this a curſed Trade for ſuch Men to uſe, that have ſworn to be true both to the King and County, and that profeſs themſelves to be both Loyal Men, and Proteſtants?</p>
               <p>But now again, before I can proceed any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt Anſwer a Queſtion, which ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſounds in my Ear, and methinks I hear ſome ſay, <hi>Where could thoſe Clippers have all thoſe vaſt and great Sums of Money to Clip; all of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> could never be their own, and therefore it muſt be that they were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by ſome great Monyed-Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer: Undoubtedly they were ſo ſupply'd by many of our great Money Maſters, who were very Rich; or ſuch as have always to command vaſt and large Sums of Money, as great Bankers, great Uſurers, great Merchants, and ſome other great Receivers of Money; and alſo ſome great Rich Trades-men of other Callings: For all theſe ſorts of Men have always by them, or at their commands, great and large Sums of Money. And alſo, they all of them, had a more commodious way, and better opportunities to put off all ſuch Clipp'd and Falſe Coin'd Money, than any other ſorts of men could have had, if there then had been any other ſorts of Men that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34674:11"/>then would have taken on them the like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Trade. But now upon the whole, I ſay, I am apt to believe, that many of thoſe Clippers, and ſome of thoſe Falſe Coiners, that have been juſtly executed for ſuch Facts, were but the hired Servants of ſome ſuch Men, as are before mentioned, yet truſty Servants to ſuch Maſters; for they would rather dye with a Lye in their Mouths, than confeſs who ſet them on work.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot otherwiſe, but comment on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſay, Great pity it is, and by all good M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, undoubtedly, it is much lamented, that we ſhould be ſo unhappy to ſee the Devil and ſuch wicked Men more truly ſerved, (by theſe their wicked Servants) than God and our King is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by too many thouſands of our Nation, that outwardly to the World profeſs much Zeal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and much Loyalty towards our King; and yet are not in their Hearts ſo faithfully zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous towards God, or ſo loyal towards our King, as thoſe poor Wretches, that ſo juſtly ſuffered, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re to their moſt wicked Maſters; I mean ſuch Rich men, as aforeſaid, and the Devil.</p>
               <p>But now again, I ſeem to hear the ſound of a Voice, that doth propoſe to me this Queſtion, <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o are thoſe Men that have thus wickedly done? What are their particular Names?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Queſtion I now Anſwer, and ſay; As for their Names, I do not readily know all of them; but ſome of them I think I may know: However, I muſt at preſent moſt humbly beg Your moſt Gratious Majeſty and the Parliament to excuſe me, tho' I do not now mention the Names of thoſe Men that have thus done, whom
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34674:11"/>I may know, and that for this Reaſon; if I ſhould here name them particularly, and after that, I ſhould fail of ſuch aſſiſtance, (as I now expect) to withſtand ſuch potent Enemies, then I am apt to believe, after ſuch failure, their Money, which anſwereth all things, will drive my Truth to the Wall with diſdain, when ſuch groſs Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhall walk the broad Streets in Pomp, with praiſe and honour amongſt Men; and then it ſhall paſs for truth, as if they were Innocent, and my ſelf Guilty of accuſing them maliciouſly, and wrongfully. And by my own experience I can ſpeak it for a truth, That I have known the like of this, which I now doubt of, done in other Cauſes; for with my Eyes and Ears have I ſeen and heard ſome Men for large Fees, devoutly Plead for wrong Cauſes, and at laſt, have by their ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and crafty Arguments, overthrown Truth; and therefore I think no Man ought to blame me for endeavouring to be as Wiſe as a Serpent, whilſt I intend to be as harmleſs as a Dove.</p>
               <p>But methinks I hear another Queſtion ask'd of me, which is this, <hi>Were there no other ſorts of Men concerned in ſuch Frauds and Cheats, as you ſeemingly lay to the Charge of ſome great Brankers, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers, great Merchants, great Receivers of Money, and ſome other great Rich Trades-men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; I am apt to believe there were then concerned in ſuch Frauds and Cheats, about ſuch Moneys, as aforeſaid, ſome Men of all ſorts of Trades, Occupations, or Profeſſions, that then had Money, or drove any manner of Trade, had a ſnack of the Benefit of it, more or leſs, ſome way or other; and ſo at laſt, ſome ſorts
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34674:12"/>of all ſuch great and ſmall Traders on Money, as aforeſaid, agreed altogether to make a clear ſcrable, or ſcramble of it, (if I may ſo call it,) or more plain, I mean every one of theſe Traders on Money, both the Sellers and Buyers of it, every one of them, catch'd what profit they could out of it, during the whole time, which they could have for ſo doing and ſo at laſt amongſt them, they have made our Land a poor <hi>England</hi> to many thouſands of Your Majeſty's poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of true Loyal Subjects: For by theſe, and ſome other ſuch-like ways as theſe are, ſuch (and ſome other ſuch like vile Miſcreants) have made themſelves extraordinary Rich, and alſo thereby brought the major part of Your Majeſty's middle, and meaneſt ſorts of good Subjects into great ſtraits and extream Poverty: And is there no way to remedy this in time, e'er it be too late? Pray, great Sirs, I moſt humbly beg of You, for God's ſake, and for Your own ſakes, now take Compaſſion on the poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of true Loyal Subjects.</p>
               <p>But here an Objection may ariſe, and it may be ſaid, <hi>I cannot think that the middle, and meaneſt ſorts of People could be ſuch Loſers, in and by the Revolution of our late Coin; for it did not then lie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much in their Hands, but most of it then lay in the Hands and Custodies of Rich Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; I acknowledge that moſt of the late Coin then did, as the new Coin now doth lie moſtly in the Hands of Rich Men; and that the poor, middle, and meaneſt ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then had, and always conſequently muſt have the leaſt ſhare of our Coin in their cuſtody; yet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34674:12"/>that doth not any way make void, or diſanul my Aſſertion: For tho' the poor, middle, and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorts of People had then the leaſt ſhare of it, whilſt it was paſſable, yet by the cunning contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of ſome Rich Men, and alſo by the Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine Ways of ſome other ſuch men as I have herein before-mentioned, and in ſome meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, they at laſt, ſome by one way, and ſome by other ways, caſt almoſt the whole Loſs and Burthen of it on the middle and poorer ſort of People in our Nation.</p>
               <p>And now (for the full Proof and better Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of this) I muſt of neceſſity now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into ſome Particulars, which I cannot well do at this time, having (as I have already ſaid) neither time nor room to ſpecifie them in, except I ſhould proceed to make this my Work ſwell to be a conſiderable Volume, which I am not now willing to do, nor perhaps will Your Greatneſs then have time nor patience to peruſe it: And therefore I muſt forbear to proceed on ſo many particulars as I could offer, and muſt now cut ſhort my Work, and firſt of all anſwer the laſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Objection.</p>
               <p>And now in Anſwer to it, I ſay; After that ſuch Men (as aforeſaid) had ſcattered all, or almoſt of all the ſuch Monies, as aforeſaid; then at a jump preſently they cry'd it down, and would not take it in any manner of Payment, or for any manner of Commodity, long before the ſeveral Limitations of Your Majeſty's then Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the taking of Clipt Monies was expired; and by that means, the greateſt part of ſuch Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies then lay in the middle and meaneſt ſorts of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34674:13"/>Trades-mens Hands, and in the hands of their poor Servants; and alſo (much of it) lay in the Hands of ſome Gentlemen and their Servants; as alſo in the hands of Farmers, Juſt manholders, and the poor Servants under them. And thus, amongſt all ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuch ſmall Money, as aforeſaid, was ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and then lay in their Hands for a while, until they grew weary of it, for it was then of no more uſe to them than Bullion: But then in a little time after that the Shop-keepers, ſuch as were by trades Grocers, Mercers, Woollen and Linnen-Drapers, and all other ſorts of Dealers, in any other ſorts of Commodities, gave out their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, or Proclamations, by Word of Mouth, that they would then take all ſuch ſorts of ſmall Moneys for Goods, tho' never ſo ſmall; And <hi>tho' no bigger than a Grain of Wheat,</hi> was the very words of ſome of them, as I was then Creditably informed: And yet nevertheleſs, they would then take it for Goods, until ſuch a time was paſt, which they then limited; And then preſently after that, all ſorts of People, both of Cities, Towns, Villages, Cottages, and all the remote Country-dwellings, hearing of this, were glad of ſuch an opportunity to put off their Bad Money, and then ſuch Trades-men had for a while a ſwinging Trade indeed, and profit enough by it, far beyond all manner of good conſcionable gain; for they all of them, from one to the other, then took Eighteen Pence for that Commodity, which at other times they would willingly have ſold for Nine Pence, Ten Pence, or Eleven Pence; and alſo took Half a Crown for that Commodity,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34674:13"/>which at other times they would have ſold for Fifteen Pence, Sixteen Pence, or Seventeen Pence: And by this way ſome ſorts of People, did then put off their ſmall Money; But the Poor and meaneſt ſorts of People could not then ſpare their ſuch Money to buy Commodites with it; for they Poor, Miſerable, and ſad Diſtreſſed Souls, then wanted it to buy Bread; and therefore they, (poor Creatures) inſtead of buying of Commodities, they were forced to ſell their Money; and for their Shilling, each of them could then have but ſix pence or ſeven pence for it, if it were of the ſmaller ſort; and but eight pence, nine pence, or ten pence for the very largeſt Shillings, after the time was over that ſuch Old Money would not paſs.</p>
               <p>And now I could deſcend into particulars, had I time and room, to let Your Moſt Gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the Parliament know, how many times theſe poor Souls, then ſold their ſmall and larger ſorts of Money from time to time, and over and over again it did then come round to their Hands, and that by means of ſuch wicked and clandeſtine ways, as they the Grocers, Mercers, and other Money-buyers then did uſe, only to gratifie their own baſe covetous Deſires. And thus were the Poor then at that time moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly oppreſt; for always, as often as ever this Money came to their Hands, tho' round, round and round again, yet ſtill they the ſaid Poor were then forced to put it off by a loſing way; for then at that time, for every Shilling, they then did twelve or fourteen penny-worth of Work for it, before they had it. And then again, they muſt fell this Shilling for ſix pence or ſeven pence, if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34674:14"/>it were a ſmall Shilling; and the Half Crowns then yielded them but ſixteen pence, eighteenpence, or twenty pence: And thus the Poor then ſold their Money to the then Money-buyers, which ſame Money-buyers did then conſtantly ſupply thoſe Searge-makers with Money, who kept thoſe poor People on work; and that in and by this way and manner, as I ſhall herein preſently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet forth.</p>
               <p>And firſt of all I ſay, the Serage-makers by trade, they then, by reaſon of the ſcarcity of Broad Money, were then forced to take Bills inſtead of Money, for their Searges; and then they (thoſe Searge-makers) did then exchange ſuch Bills with the Shop-keepers, as Grocers, Mercers, and other Trades-men, who did then ſupply the Searge-makers with Money; and that in and by this way and manner, as followeth.</p>
               <p>When they the Searge-makers, or any of them, had occaſion to exchange a <hi>Bill,</hi> either of ten pounds, twenty pounds, or thirty pounds value; then the Searge-maker, went to one of thoſe Grocers, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, or other Trades-men, and gives in his Bill preſent in Hand, to be paid in Twenty, Thirty, or Forty Shillings a Week, Week after Week, until the full value of his Bill be paid him: But now note, this Bill ſo given by the Searg-maker, was then preſently good to the Grocer, Mercer, or any other Trades-man, as any Currant rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Money in their Pocket, tho' he the ſaid Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, Mercer, or any other Trades-man, then paid the value of this Bill to the Searge-maker, but by Twenty, Thirty, or Forty Shillings by the Week.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34674:14"/>
               <p>But now again, here lyeth the mean Query of the matter; <hi>In and with what ſort of Coin did thoſe then Mercers, Grocers, or others, then pay the Searge-makers for their Bills ſo given to them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; They the then Grocers, Mercers, or others, did then pay ſuch Bills to the then Searge-makers all in ſuch Money, as they or any of them then bought from the Poor, Hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Daily and Weekly, which Moneys did not coſt they the ſaid Grocers, Mercers, or other buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Money, above eight pence, nine pence, or ten pence, (the Shilling) and yet, they (the ſaid Grocers, Mercers, and other ſuch Buyers of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney) had then that little Conſcience within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as to pay back again from time to time, to the Searg-makers in their Weekly payments, for their Bills, the ſame Money which they then bought up, at ſuch cheap Rates, Hourly, Daily and Weekly from the Poor, from time to time; I ſay, the ſame Money, they the ſaid Grocers, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and other ſuch then buyers of Money, did then pay it unto the Searg-makers, in its full va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, as it was firſt coined for; which ſame Money the then Searg-makers, were forced then to pay it unto their Poor Labouring Servants alſo, in its full value, as it was Coined for, and that becauſe they the then Searg-makers ſo received it for their Bills, in their Weekly payments, from thoſe ſaid Grocers, Mercers, and other ſuch Money-buyers as are before mentioned, in my foregoing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</p>
               <p>But now again, here comes the Tradegy of the matter at laſt, for 'twas the Poor Labouring Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that then were the greateſt Loſers all the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34674:15"/>while; for they Poor Souls, every Week had ſome of the ſame Money came round to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again, which Moneys, they aways bought very dear; and yet then were forced always to fell it very cheap; for then when it circulated round to the ſaid Grocers, Mercers, and other Shop-keepers hands again, then they would give the aforeſaid Poor for their ſuch Moneys, but barely their old Prices for it, which was but eight pence, nine pence or ten pence for their Shilling; and thus by ſuch ways and means, as I have herein deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, ſuch Moneys, as aforeſaid, conſequently and conſtantly came round, and round, and round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>again, and again, to the ſore loſs and damage of Poor diſtreſſed Labours, as I have herein deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, whoſe Gauled Backs, have yet on them pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified Sores to this very day, by means of ſuch moſt grievous Burthens, as were then laid upon them, And thus by ſuch Clandeſtine ways and means, as I have herein deſcribed, then did many Rich covetous Cormorants, with their Deviliſh Wheels of Craft, then break the Poor to pieces. O moſt abominable Wretches! that had then in them no more Charity for their then Poor Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fellow-Creatures: And are not ſuch Actions as aforeſaid, grand Oppreſſions, and ſuch Profits and Gains, are they not moſt abominable Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? or are not ſuch things abſolute Grindings of the Faces of the Poor? And yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, ſuch Oppreſſors and Grinders of the Faces of the Poor, think themſelves ſafe, becauſe they think within themſelves, that no Law can Reach them to puniſh them for it; But however the Juſt God of Heaven will at laſt, give them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34674:15"/>and all ſuch as them are, their due Rewards. But yet again, I ſay, I cannot otherwiſe but admire at the Impudence of ſuch vile Miſcreants, that have done ſuch things, and yet, at the ſame time have then profeſt themſelves to be preciſe <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and alſo devout Loyal Men; But let any Judicious Man, or Men, judge what Principles ſuch Men then were of, or may now or hereafter be of, as to matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and as to their Loyalty they then were, and low are, and I believe hereafter will be, pure Subjects indeed, even ſuch as will turn any way, that either the Wind or Tide, of their own baſe Intereſt, will moſt eaſily drive them.</p>
               <p>But again, during the whole time of the ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Money amongſt ſuch poor People as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, yet Corn, and all other neceſſary Proviſions, were then extream dear; and therefore how could it be otherwiſe, but hard Times with ſuch poor Creatures. O! were not thoſe Times meer Starving Times? yes, they were, and I believe that then at that time, many Hundreds, if not Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, throughout <hi>England,</hi> gradually were then nearly Starved to Death; for with my own Eyes did I then ſee, in our ſaid Town of <hi>Tiverton,</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> many Poor, Weak, Languiſhing Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then walking up and down the Street, and many of them in a ſhort time after that Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whoſe Diſtempers originally, (I believe) firſt proceeded from no other Cauſes than from the want of Neceſſary Food; which Food ſuch poor Creatures, whilſt alive, could no way have it, for want of Money: For Charity was then, as it is now, very Cold. But for Corn, altho' it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34674:16"/>was then ſo very dear, yet there was then enough in our Land, and the then Corn-ſellers could then aford their Corn at reaſonable Prices, but they would not. And thus by the means of ſome Mens obdurate Hearts in them times, many were then mearly Starved to Death, in the midſt of an indifferent Plenty; for throughout our Land one where with the other, we have always hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to had enough of all ſorts of Proviſion, tho' not in ſuch great Plenty, as in times paſt we have had, and I do heartily wiſh, that at laſt our Sins may not bring on us a Scarcity indeed, Read the whole 5th Chap. of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> throughout, but more particularly obſerve, verſes 4.5. and 25.</p>
               <p>And therefore, Great Sirs. I moſt humbly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, for God's ſake, and for Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſake, as well as for your own dear ſakes now forthwith take ſome compaſſion on the Poor, Middle, and Meaneſt ſorts of true Loyal <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects, who are yet driven to great ſtraits, and many of them now, at this preſent time, under great Wants.</p>
               <p>But now again, after all the then ſcattering abroad ſuch (before mentioned) diminiſhed and corrupted ſorts of Coin, you may find by my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing Arguments, and by my propoſing and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of Queſtions, it now ſeems very likely, that then at laſt, a great quantity of that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Coin was again reduc'd into the Hands of ſuch Buyers of Money, and other ſuch Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as I have already before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>And now the next Query that naturally flows from all my former Diſcourſes, I think muſt be this; <hi>What did thoſe ſeveral Shop-keepers, and all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34674:16"/>thoſe other petty Buyers of Money then do with ſuch Money (as aforeſaid) at laſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; I believe all of them well knew, before-hand, how to put it off then at that time: And I am apt to believe alſo, that they (all of them) then had Commiſſions from ſome great Bankers, or great Receivers of Money, or great Merchants, or great and ſmall Cuſtom-Officers, or ſome other Officers of or belonging to the Duty of <hi>Exciſe;</hi> or ſome other great Rich Men, that could lend great Sums of Money to ſome other Men to buy up ſuch ſmall Money for them; for I am ſure ſome of thoſe Men that then bought up great quantities of ſuch ſmall corrupted Money, were then very poor in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and had then no ſtock of Money of their own; and therefore it muſt be that ſuch poor Villains as then bought up ſuch great quantities of this then ſmall corrupted Coin, did then buy it up, to and for the uſes of ſuch Rich Men, who would not then appear in ſuch Actions themſelves in Perſon; but by and with their Money, they did then appear, and then gave Commiſſions to ſuch poor Villains to buy up all ſuch ſmall Moneys as they could get for them. And for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the truth of this, I am apt to believe that there are ſome Men that can give teſtimony of the truth of all that I have here ſaid: But they will not. And again, I ſay, I am apt to believe, that there are ſome other Perſons, that will tell the truth of all that they do know, in, or of ſuch matters, (as aforeſaid) if at any time they are thereto called ſo to do.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34674:17"/>
               <p>But now upon the whole, I ſay again, I am apt to believe that ſuch ſorts of great Rich Men, (as aforeſaid) had at laſt amongſt them, by ſome way or other, all the then ſuch ſmall Moneys, that the Money-buyers, Grocers, Mercers, and other Shop-keepers, then bought up and ſo received from time to time: And alſo, I am apt to believe that ſome of thoſe then Money-buyers, and Shop-keepers, did then put off their ſuch Monies on very good terms, and with great profit, eſpecially ſuch of them as could ſtay for their Money, until the Money-Merchant's returns could come about: But the then petty Chapmen of the Money-buyers, and other ſmall Shop-keepers, that could not for bear their Money, until the great Money-Merchant's returns could come about, ſuch as them, were the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forced to put off their ſuch Monies for ſmaller profit, and that only becauſe they could not then ſtay for their Money, until the ſaid Money-Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant's returns could come about.</p>
               <p>But now again, methinks I now hear a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Queſtion asked of me, and it doth now ſeem to ſound in my Ears, as if I did now hear ſome one ſay to me, <hi>Suppoſe ſuch Men, as are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, did then ſo get in all, or almoſt of all the then Monies, as aforeſaid, into their own Hands or Cuſtodies, what could they then do with it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; I cannot tell all the ways that they then had for the putting off ſuch ſmall Monies at laſt: But undoubtedly they all of them had then a way for it, or otherwiſe they would not then have been ſo greedy after it, as they then were in the getting in of it then into their own Hands.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34674:17"/>
               <p>But now upon the whole of this Argument, if I may be permitted to ſpend my Thoughts upon it, and ſpeak my own Opinion in and about the whole matter, as I verily believe it to be; Then I will ſay, that I believe ſome of the aforeſaid ſuch Monies, was then paid into Your Majeſty's uſe for Cuſtoms, and ſome for Exciſe, and ſome for Taxes, and ſome by way of Lones; and ſo then at laſt, ſome by one way, and ſome by other ways, it was all, or almoſt all of it, lodged in Your moſt Gratious Majeſty's Exchequer, and there (I believe) was at laſt found much to light. But the Perjuries of ſuch Men, as might not then do Your Majeſty and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try right; they, for ought I know, are lodged in Hell, and there to abide until the great Day of Judgment, and then may riſe again as Witneſſes againſt them, except (in the mean time) ſuch Men make Reſtitution for the great Wrongs they have done, whilſt they are here living upon the Earth.</p>
               <p>And now to conclude this ſecond part of my Diſcourſe, I cannot otherwiſe but ſay, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all thoſe evil and moſt pernitious minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, (before-mentioned) and in ſome meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſcribed, there was not then amongſt them, as much as one of them, that I do call here by the Name of Your Majeſty's poor, middle, and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorts of true Loyal Subjects, then any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in theſe (before-mentioned) moſt horrid and wicked Actions: But they who were then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in ſuch aforeſaid wicked Actions, were Men of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther Ranks, and Degrees, and Qualifications in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir Minds, as well as in their then ſuch Actions: And in their Eſtates, they (many of them) then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34674:18"/>were, and now are conſiderably Rich; tho' not ſo very Rich as ſome in the World are; but I mean ſome of them then were, and now are, ſuch a ſort of Rich Men, as we poor Country-Folks here amongſt us do call them rich, topping, towering Men; and ſuch Men as have all of them taken the <hi>Oaths of Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy;</hi> and they do ſay, all of them, that they will fight for Your Majeſty and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and the good of their Country. But who can believe them? if thoſe Reaſons which I ſhall here now offer, be but well and duly conſidered.</p>
               <p>And now I ſay, 'tis viſibly ſeen, and by their Actions too notoriuoſly known, that ſuch Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Men, as aforeſaid, have always had from time to time, baſe, wretched, and Self-intreſted Hearts; and to ſave their own Money, they will do almoſt any thing in the world; and alſo, in and by a baſe, Hypocritical, Undermining, and Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine Way, they will uſe all manner of Fraud that their moſt Wicked Hearts can invent, to get Riches, altho' at the ſame time (in their own Hearts) they muſt then needs be ſenſible that ſuch Actions are the ready ways and means to pull down true Religion, and overthrow the King, and ruin our Country: And therefore, I ſay, can any Soul believe, that ſuch Men, as will for the Love of Money, deceive our King, and ruin our Country, that they will ever fight for the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> and King, and Country; no, no, for I am apt to believe that they will rather, every man of them, forſake the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and leave our King and Country to the mercy of an Enemy, than fight for any Religion, King, or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34674:18"/>Country whatſoever: And therefore I think it not ſafe for any one, to put to much Truſt in any ſuch Men, that at the beſt are but like great Sticks, that are ſo much rotten, as that no man may dare venture the weight of his whole Body upon them, unleſs he be ſo careleſs of himſelf, as that he doth not value a Fall to the Ground by them. But however, amongſt ſuch men, ſome of them perhaps will fight with a Thief in the Night, rather than they will loſe all their Money; and that only becauſe ſuch men adore and love their Money, more than they do love God or Religion, the King or Country; for ſuch men ſeldom regard any one's good but their own: Nay, in fine, I ſay, if all things are but well and duly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſuch men do not at all, by doing ſuch Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, truly love themſelves. And thus I end the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of my Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>But <hi>3dly.</hi> There is one other fore Grievance which of late hath, and now doth continually damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all Your Majeſty's Poor, Middle, Meaneſt ſorts of Subjects; and that is, the loſs of Trade, for ever ſince the time that, that moſt curſed Trade of Buying and Selling of Money was firſt ſet up, all other honeſt Trades have ever ſince been decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; But if ſuch vile Miſcreants had then been ſuch good Men, as to have then Imploy'd all their Stocks in a way of honeſt Trading, to keep the Poor then on Work, than for ought I know, Trading might have continued good to this Day; or if they had then at that time, but ſo Imploy'd their Wits in making all manner of honeſt ſhifts, to keep the Poor on work, as they then did in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34674:19"/>ſtudying out all manner of knaviſh Ways, that ever their baſe covetous Hearts could then think on, to make a meer prey on the Poor, only to gratifie their own unſatiable deſires, that they then had after their filthy Lucre, and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concionable Gain; Then certainly, their would never have been ſuch miſerable Times as then were and now are to this very day: For when Mens Actions do pleaſe God, then his Bleſſings do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly attend ſuch mens undertakings; But when Men, under pretence of doing all manner of Good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o then all manner of Evil, what then can ſuch Men expect from the Hands of God, otherwiſe than his Wrath to follow them, until it hath overtaken them. And therefore, I now adviſe all ſuch Men as have ſo done, forth with to repent them of their Evil doings, and alſo to make ſpeedy Reſtitution, in the beſt way and manner, that they now can make, leſt the Cries of the Poor do at laſt aſcend up into Heaven, and from thence bring down Vengeance on Earth, and on the Heads of ſuch Men, as have thus from time to time ſo oppreſt the Poor; for they certainly, did by their curſed Money-trade deſtroy all other Trades; And therefore at their Doors it ought to be laid; tho' the ſad effects of it doth yet ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main on the now living Poor to this very day.</p>
               <p>But again, ſuch covetous Rich Men, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, did then ſo act, as if they had then been wholly bent to bring future Poverty upon our whole Nation, for they then took all advantage for their own Profit on all ſorts of People, but more eſpecially on the Poor, Middle, and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorts of People, and that becauſe they could
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34674:19"/>more eaſily then make a Prey of them, than of others; and as if Sorrow had been then on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſs added to their Afflictions. So then thoſe great Loſſes came on the Poor, Midle, and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſorts of People, in the very time of their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Need; for Taxes then were very high, and hore heavy on them, and then it was in that very nick of time, that thoſe vile Men made their Market on them, and a Prey of them. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this (ſad times) it was then for the Poor, becauſe then they had not half ſo much work as they could do, nor ſcarce half the worth of their Hire for it when they had done it; for then moſt of the Poor of our ſaid Town of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire,</hi> wrought by way of Truck; and inſtead of Money for Work, they had then moſt of them only Commodities, as Kerſie, Drugget, Serge, and Linnen-Cloath, or the like of other Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities: But then, after they had received ſuch Commodities for their Work, in leu of Money, then after that they ſpent much of their time in going abroad to Sell ſuch Commodities; And then when they had Sold them, many times they had for them but little more than half the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of them; and then, with this little Money they did buy Bread, after the rate of Ten, and Eleven Shillings the Buſhel for Wheat, and Four or Five Shillings the Buſhel for Barley.</p>
               <p>And now judge you, Great Sirs, were not thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es meer Starving times? Yes, God knows to many poor Souls then found them ſo, who are now in their Graves; and hard times it is ſtill, with many of the Poor now living. And therefore, I now moſt humbly beſeech Your moſt Gracious
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34674:20"/>Majeſty, and the Parliament, to believe me in what I have here ſaid, for it is the very Truth.</p>
               <p>But <hi>4thly.</hi> I cannot otherwiſe but make known to Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this ſore Greviance alſo, and that is, how heavy, and ſorely, the Taxes of Births and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, hath of late, and now doth lie on the Poor: But as for Perſons of Quallity and other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as alſo (many other Rich Men) that want Children to Injoy what they have, it muſt needs be great comfort to them, to have the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to pay Birth-Taxes; and if Death-Taxes be at any time due from any of them, then they can very eaſily pay it without any manner of loſs to themſelves, if they will but obſerve this rule for it, firſt to reckon with themſelves how much Money their Death-Taxes will amount to, and then ſo much Money as their Death-Taxes come to, they may very well keep back and ſave it, out of the Extravagant Expences of their Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; And that way they will be no Loſers at all by their paying to the King Death-Taxes: But for the Poor ſo to pay, is to them very grievous, for there are many Thouſands in <hi>England</hi> that have not the Alms of the Pariſh, that are in ſuch miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conditions, by means of the late and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hard times, that they have ſcarce Swaddling-Cloathes to wrap up their new Born Babes in, when they come into the World, nor ſcarce Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to buy Bread for ſuch little Ones, as they had before: And then ſome times, it may be that ſome of thoſe poor little Innocent Creatures dye meerly for want of ſuch Neceſſary Food, as they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34674:20"/>ſhould have; And then their comes both to one time Birth-Money and Death-Money to be paid; and pay it they muſt; And this drives ſuch Poor to great ſtreights, for then ſome of them are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſell ſome of their Houſhold-goods to raiſe Money to pay ſuch Taxes? O (ſad) it is with them, and beyond my capacity to find Words ſuitable to ſet forth all their Grievances and Troubles, which many Thouſands in <hi>England</hi> of late have, and now do Labour under them.</p>
               <p>And therefore I will trouble Your moſt Gratious Majeſty, and the Parliament, no farther in theſe Diſcourſes, but will conclude all their Complaints of this nature, in theſe one or two true Stories, which I heard, as it came from the Mouth of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat was a Gatherer of the Taxes for Births and Burials.</p>
               <p>And now, firſt of all, I ſay, in our Town of <hi>Tiverton,</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> there was a Poor Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat buried a Child, and when the then Receiver <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Burial-Taxes came to him for the Tax-Money, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue on the Death of his Child, he (the poor man) paid the ſaid Money; and then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiver of ſuch Tax-money, lookt round about the Poor man's Houſe, to find a Place to lay his Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, that he might then write down the ſaid Poor Man's Name, and the Sum he then received from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his poor man. But he the then Receiver of ſuch Tax-Money, ſeeing in this poor man's Houſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Table, Board, Cheſt, Bench, or Stool, or any place for him to reſt his Book on; he then ſaid to this Poor Man, <hi>I think I must go away, and not write down thy Name now; for here is no place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n all thy Houſe for me to write upon.</hi> Then this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34674:21"/>Poor Man hearing that, replyed, <hi>Pray Maſter don't you go away, and not write down my Name; for if you pleaſe Maſter, I will turn me about, and ſtoop forward, and then you may reſt your Book upon my Back, and ſo write down my Name, and how much Money you have received from me.</hi> And ſo this poor man immediately ſo ſtoopt down, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver of ſuch Tax-Monies did then reſt his Book on the ſaid poor man's Back, whilſt he the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver wrote down the poor man's Name, and the Sum he then received of him. And thus I end my firſt true Story.</p>
               <p>My ſecond true Story is this; There was alſo a poor Widow Woman of our ſaid Town of <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who had buried ſeveral Children within ſome ſhort time together: And when the then Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of ſuch Tax-Monies came to her Houſe for ſuch Taxes, ſhe the poor Widow Woman had not the Money at that time to pay him: But ſhe promiſed the then Receiver to bring the ſaid Money to him at his own Houſe, as ſoon as ſhe could get it; which in ſome time after that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhe did: But then immediately after ſhe had paid ſuch Monies to the then Receiver of ſuch Taxes, ſhe the poor Widow Woman wept betterly, &amp; then ſolemnly proteſted to the then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver's Wife, That then at that time ſhe had not one penny-worth of Proviſion in her Houſe, not could ſhe then command one Penny more in the whole World to buy Bread for her ſelf or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then left living; the thoughts of which made ſhe the poor Widow Woman, again at that time weep moſt bitterly; and then wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Hands together, with her Eyes lifted up to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34674:21"/>Heaven-wards, ſhe then with great grief ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe words, <hi>Good God! was there ever any ſuch thing as this ever done in the World before until now?</hi> And then forthwith, ſhe the ſaid poor Widow Woman, went homeward, bitterly La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting her ſelf.</p>
               <p>And now upon the conſideration of this, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe but ſay, Undoubtedly the Cries of many of our good, poor miſerable Souls have already aſcended up into Heaven; and therefore, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ope, their Cries will now forth-with be heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Ears of Men on Earth, and ſo ſpeedily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave ſome Relief.</p>
               <p>And now, <hi>5thly.</hi> I cannot otherwiſe, but make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown to Your Moſt Gracious Majeſty, and the Parliament, how one other moſt horrid Crime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath of late been committed, and ſtill is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly uſed and practiſed by too many Men, in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation, which Crime is a moſt wicked Trade, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at for ſome Years paſt, and now preſent, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch uſed; And that is, to buy up vaſt and great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uantities of Corn beforehand, only to Regrate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon it, and ſo by ſuch means do create a Dearth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen there is a Plenty in our Land, and their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay and manner of doing it, is this; As ſoon as Harveſt approacheth, that the Country-man can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e how Corn is ſped in kerning; Then preſently our Rich, Covetuous, cloſe-Fiſted Gentlemen, and Rich clowniſh grubing Farmers, and ſome Rich Covetuous Merchants, that neither Plow nor Sow: all thoſe ſorts of Men then take their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation to ride and walk abroad to overlook their Neighbours Fields, as well as their own, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey obſerve who has the beſt Corn, as well as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34674:22"/>whoſe is the worſt; And then when they have thus fully viewed the Country round them, then in the next place they make it their Buſineſs, to go to the ſeveral Houſes of their Tenants, and other Juſtman-holders, that are not ſo well ſtockt in Money as themſelves are, and then raiſe a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about Corn, how it is kerned, and alſo what Fields are well kerned, and what Fields are but lightly kerned. And then after this, the next Queſtion that thoſe Country-Gentlemen, or Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, or Merchants, or other Buyers of Corn do ask, is what Rate they think Corn will ſell at by the Buſhel the Year following? Then the poor honeſt Tenant or Juſtman-holder ſpeaks plainly his mind, as he then thinks by the goodneſs of it as it then appeareth in the Fields, when Harveſ is juſt at hand, and the Corn paſt the danger o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ruſt or Canker, and very good, only left to the Mercy of God, and the Weather, and ſo he give his Judgment what he thinks the Price by the Buſhel will be the Year following. But then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the Country-Gentleman, or Farmer, or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, or other Buyers ſo concern'd, <hi>Tuſh Man, cannot go to ſuch a Price, as thee tells of, for Corn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> well ſped.</hi> But then ſays the poor honeſt Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Indeed Maſter</hi> (with his Hat off, and ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Head) <hi>methinks, Master, it ſhould go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Price by the Buſhel that I tell you. No, no,</hi> (ſaith the Rich Country Gentleman, or Rich Grubin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Farmer, or Covetous Merchant,) <hi>it will not go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that Price this Year. But come</hi> (ſay they, or an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one of them) <hi>what need we any more talk about this What wot thee take for all the Corn thou haſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ground this Year; for to have all thy Money together
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34674:22"/>(perhaps) will do thee a great kindneſs.</hi> To which the Poor Country-Man anſwers with a ſmile, and all this while (perhaps) his Hat is off; and in his Hand, (or) he holds it behind his Poll, (or) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Arm; and then ſays, <hi>Money altogether, (Maſter!) will do me more kindneſs than to carry it into the Market, to ſell it out there by the Buſhel.</hi> And thus ſuch poor Country men, only reſerve for themſelves as much Corn as they think may be enough to ſerve their turn, both in Bread and Drink, and ſo ſell away the reſt all to a lump; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umping Bargains they have (many of them) that buy up Corn in this way and manner: For the poor honeſt Country-man reckoneth to himſelf now he can afford it, according to the Rent he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ays for his Ground; and according to the coſt he hath laid out in it: And thus ſuch poor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men are very well contented with ſuch honeſt Gain.</p>
               <p>And thus, by ſuch ways and means as theſe, ſome ſuch Men, as aforeſaid, have of late Years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought up great and vaſt quantities of Corn; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen, when once ſuch Men have got it into their Clutches, they will not ſuffer it to be brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto the Markets (until) ſuch times as their Corn is ſpent, that do uſually bring in Corn to apply the Market. And thus, by means of ſuch Men, and ſuch Actions, as aforeſaid, our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of late Years have always lookt thin of Corn, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the midſt of Plenty. And if this be always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffered, for ſuch men ſo to do, (then) there will ever hereafter be, a continual Dearth on Corn, let what plenty ſoever come, (yet) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34674:23"/>that, we muſt expect it always to be very dear; for by theſe, and other ſuch-like ways as theſe are, ſuch Men will get almoſt all the Corn in our Land, every Year, Year after Year, into their own Hands; and then they will have their own great Prices for it, or they will keep it back out of the Market from time to time, and from year to year, until it doth become Mouldy, (or Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty) and almoſt ready to Stink, ſo as that it will be then ſcarce fit for the uſe of Men, or until Rats and Mice have devoured a great part of it.</p>
               <p>And thus thoſe greedy Cormorants lay up Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Mice,</hi> and thereby (meerly) ſtarve many good Chriſtians; and all this is for filthy Lucre's-ſake, and to heap up to themſelves the Treaſures of this World, which at laſt they muſt leave it all behind them, and ſo depart hence with a gauled Conſcience, by means thereof (or at leaſt) have a Curſe on it, unto the third and fourth Generation of their Poſterity: And the truth of this I muſt believe, becauſe God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath ſaid in his Second <hi>Commandment,</hi> That he will viſit the Iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them that hate him. And who are they that hate God? (Why) ſuch as grind the Faces of the Poor, and make their Prey on the Needy, and laugh when their Calamity comethy upon them. And ſuch Actions as theſe, (ſuch) Corn-ſellers, as aforeſaid, have oftentimes uſed towards the Poor, when they have come into the Market to buy their Corn of them; for with my Eyes I have ſeen ſuch (Corn-ſellers) very rude towards poor People, and becauſe they would
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34674:23"/>not come up preſently to their great Prices, they the ſaid Corn-ſellers, (ſome of them) have with their Hands, thruſt them off from their Corn-Tubs, and then, after ſuch hard uſage, they the poor Corn-buyers, have mildly ſaid, (to the Corn-ſellers) <hi>How can you in your Conſcience ask ſo dear for your Corn?</hi> But then that word (<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>) hath put the ſaid Corn-ſellers into ſuch Cholerick Fits, as that then they have preſently took thoſe poor People by the Arms, and by their violent ſtrength, have thrown them off from their Corn-Tubs, to the very Ground it ſelf; and then in a little time after their Cholerick Fits were over, (then) they would (Impudently) Brazen out the ſaid Poor with Laughter, and then flout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly drive them away with their bruitiſh Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſaying, <hi>Go farther; away about your Buſineſs: Are you come to tell us of our Conſciences? We will have our Prices for our Corn, or you ſhall have none of us.</hi> Theſe, and many ſuch-like Actions as theſe, with my own Eyes and Ears, have I often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeen, and heard them ſo do, and ſo ſpeak.</p>
               <p>And is not this a hating of God, to deal with his poor Creatures (in ſuch) ſervile ways and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as I have herein from time to time, and from Argument to Argument, ſet forth and deſcribed? Look in <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.31. there <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the Poor, reproacheth his Maker: But he that Honoureth Him, hath Mercy on the Poor.</hi> Look alſo in <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.5. 'tis there ſaid, <hi>Whoſo mocketh the Poor, reproacheth his Maker; and he that is glad at Calamities, ſhall not be unpuniſhed.</hi> Again, I ſay, He that is Charitable to the Poor, loveth the Lord, and his Alms are acceptible, as if it were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34674:24"/>done to God himſelf: See in 25th Chap. of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, verſ. 40. 'tis there ſaid, <hi>Verily, I ſay unto you, Inaſmuch as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my Brethren, ye have done it unto me.</hi> And thus we may ſee from Chriſt's own Words, when any thing either of Mercy or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is either ſhewn or done to any of God's poor People, God takes it as done to himſelf: And if ſo, then conſequently this muſt follow, that all manner of Wrongs, or Violences, that are any way done to God's poor diſtreſſed Ones, are by God himſelf, ſo deemed and taken, as if it were done to Himſelf; as may be ſeen in the ſame 25th Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel aforeſaid, beginning at the 41 verſe, and ſo onwards to the 45th verſe, which 45th verſe ſaith, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, inaſmuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me.</hi> And now again, I ſay, then conſequently it muſt follow, that whoſoever ſhall ſee any of God's poor diſtreſſed People Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and give them no Meat; Thirſty, and give them no Drink; Naked, and cloathed them not; Sick, and in Priſon, and viſit them not, are guilty of the moſt higheſt Ingratitude: For was it not God himſelf that firſt gave to every Man all that he hath? Why then ſhould any Man be ſo ungrateful, as to deny God, ſome part of his own when he thus requires it to be given to his poor diſtreſſed People, (eſpecially) ſeeing by that way, God is willing to receive it, as if it were given to himſelf: And for the further proof of this, look (alſo) in the 19 Chapter of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> verſ. the 17. 'tis there ſaid, <hi>He that hath pitty upon the Poor,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34674:24"/>Lendeth unto the Lord; and that which he hath given, will he pay him again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe things, few Men now do take into their Conſideration; for in this our Age, Men are now come to that height and degrees of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, that they then were who lived in the Days of the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> as you may ſee in his 8th Chapter, verſ. the 4th and 5th, 'tis there ſaid, <hi>Hear this O ye that ſwallow up the Needy, even to make the Poor of the Land to fail, ſaying, When will the new-Moon be gone, that we may ſell Corn, and the Sabbath, that we may ſet forth Wheat, making the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phah ſmall, and the Shekel great, and falſifying the Ballances by deceit.</hi> And for better ſatisfaction, you may Read the whole 8th Chapter of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Amos,</hi> and there you may ſee what ſore Judgments are threatned on ſuch a People as ſo do.</p>
               <p>And now laſt of all, I Recommended (and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer) to the ſerious peruſal of all Men, the whole 28th Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and there may be ſeen what Bleſſings the great God of Heaven and Earth, hath in ſtore for ſuch as do well, as may be ſeen in the firſt verſe of that Chapter, and ſo onwards to the 15 verſ. of the ſaid Chapter, and then Read on to the end thereof, and there you may ſee, what (Curſes) God will power down on the Heads of all thoſe that will (continually) perſiſt on in their Evil ways.</p>
               <p>But again, altho' in the Eyes of moſt Men, the greateſt loſs and danger of thoſe (Miſchievous) Actions, before-mentioned, are paſt and over; yet, I am to believe, that the moſt (malignant) part and direful effects of them are yet to come,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34674:25"/>for by Obſervation of things paſt, both in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Supernatural Cauſes, it hath been by experience found, that when the Cauſes have been out of the ſight of all Men, and (memory) of ſome Men, yet their Effects have been found and felt afterward; And to make this more plain by way of ſimilitude, I ſay, with my Eyes have I ſeen a fair flouriſhing Orchard, with delicate Bloſſoms ſprouted out with great Life and Vigour, and very likely to produce much Fruit to the Owner thereof, who (ſeemingly) upon the firſt ſight of it, did then depend upon having much Fruit that Year; but then, by the means of a few Froſty Mornings, or with ſome Blaſts of Lightning, was either withered, (or) Scorched, and ſo loſt and gone, which when the Owner thereof ſaw it, he did then within himſelf much contemplate about it, (altho) to outward appearance, it was not then to be diſcern'd by his countenance, that he was ſo very much concern'd, at his then preſent loſs, for after he had then well conſidered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, he then ſaid, <hi>Come, I have a good ſtock of old Syder left, and for Apples, I believe we ſhall not want them very much, for I believe, I ſhall have ſome tho' not ſo many, as I was in hopes of, yet enough I hope, to make ſome Chriſtmas-pyes, to feaſt my Friends.</hi> But then afterwards it ſo happened, that this Gentleman's Old ſtock of Syder was well nigh ſpent before Winter came on, and when <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> came, he had no Syder to give to his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and other Friends, that then came to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him, nor Apples enough to make <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi> Pyes, to feaſt them; and then this Gentleman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan publickly to lament the loſs of his Bloſſoms,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34674:25"/>and that becauſe by means thereof; he (then) could not accommodate his Tenants, and other of his Friends, ſo well, as otherwiſe he would have done, if his ſaid Bloſſoms in that Spring-time before, had come to their full Perfection, as to have produced good and well ripened Fruit: For this (Gentleman) whom I mean (I ſay) he is a true generous ſpirited Gentleman, and ſuch a one as is willing to oblige all Men, and to do right to every one, is my real belief of him.</p>
               <p>Again, I ſay, there was a certain Rich Man, who had in his Poſſeſſion ſeveral Mannours of Land, which were all well ſtockt, both with Horſes, Cattle, and Sheep; and alſo, he had by him much Treaſure; and to mannage theſe his Temporal Affairs, he had many Servants under him; ſome of thoſe Servants were very faithful to him; but others of them were as unfaithful to him, and yet ſo ſmooth and ſubtil in their way, as that they could not be by any way diſcerned from them that were faithful Servants to him; tho' at the ſame time (by a fair and Friend-like ſmiling kind of way) they did (Clandeſtinely) take from him much of his Treaſure: Which Loſſes, the ſaid Rich Man could no way diſcover, or avoid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem in along time after he had received them. But at laſt, (in proceſs of time) this Rich Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound that his Treaſure was much waſted, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen he called his Servants to account for it; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they, (all of them) both Good and Evil, the Faithful &amp; the Unfaithful, gave in their Accounts, which ſeem'd to the Rich Man, all Plain and Juſt; and yet at the ſame time, He (the Rich Man) well knew that ſome of them were Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34674:26"/>faithful to Him: But how to diſtinguiſh them one from the other, he could not tell, but much troubled he was about it; and Cauſe enough he had for it; for he then felt the Effects of ſuch Loſſes (as Time) had almoſt worn quite out of mind.</p>
               <p>But now, upon the whole of this matter, what can I ſay more of it than this, ſuch Evil-doings as theſe, ſometimes will be; (and yet) no Man can help it. And therefore, if any Man knows himſelf to be abuſed, and cannot help himſelf, (ſo well as he would) yet nevertheleſs I think 'tis but Prudence in any ſuch man, if he doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all manner of Lawful Means to help himſelf as well as he can, or may, in any Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Way. And now in reference to this matter, I cannot otherwiſe but ſay as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Such Sharking Wits, like (Weather-cocks) with the Wind,</l>
                  <l>So nimbly turn their Faults, no Man can find:</l>
                  <l>But Time will come, when All Things ſhall be known,</l>
                  <l>And then ſuch Wits (ſhall) quite be overthrown.</l>
                  <bibl>[<hi>Read the firſt</hi> Pſalm <hi>of</hi> David; <hi>but more particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſixth Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <p>And now may it pleaſe Your moſt <hi>Gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> and the now <hi>Honourable Parliament:</hi> By divers Ways and Methods, Arguments and Similitudes, both Metaphorically, and Really, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſet forth to Your Greatneſs, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral great Abuſes (done) from time to time, both to Your moſt Gratious <hi>(Majeſty)</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; amongſt which of them, the Poor, Middle, &amp; Meaneſt ſorts of them, have the greateſt Reaſon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34674:26"/>to complain: And to whom ſhall they complain, but to the Powers that are ordained to rule over them? And who are they, but Your moſt <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious [Majeſty]</hi> and the <hi>Parliament?</hi> And therefore I hope Your <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> (both) will be pleaſed (now) to lend an Ear to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and forthwith think on ſome way or other, that ſome Speedy Courſe may be taken for their Relief: And in ſo doing, it may be, for ought I know, not only a means to Relief their great Neceſſities, but alſo (a great means) to ſtrengthen Your moſt <hi>Gratious Majeſty</hi> againſt all Your Enemies: And therefore it is, that I have now taken upon me (to offer) unto Your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this Treatiſe, which had been more fit for ſome Eminent Perſon to have undertaken it, than for ſo mean a Perſon as I am. But I thought it an indiſpenſible Duty, and very needful for ſome (one) or other to do it, and I have long waited to ſee whether any one would do it; and then not finding (or knowing) any one that hath ſo done, therefore it was that I now at laſt reſolved on the doing of it: But whether I have done it to the content of all Perſons that may have the reading of it, I cannot tell; for I know my Capacity to be ſuch, as to want Words to pleaſe ſome Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſorts of Men: But however, I am well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented (in this my low Station) and mean De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Knowledge: And I think my ſelf more happy in being only able to Speak Truth Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, than to be able by Sophiſtical Arguments, to baffle Truth Eloquently.</p>
               <p>And again, I muſt ſay, there are ſome Men in the World, that have in them Accute Natural
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34674:27"/>Parts, and are endowed with ſharp Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and alſo, there is beſtowed on them great Riches, and all manner of Humane Learning, and yet they Exerciſe their high acquired Parts, (moſtly) in ſtudying out Critical Points, and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Arguments, that thereby they may be the better enabled (only) to confound Reaſon, and wreſt Truth: But ſuch Men, as have only in them ſuch Parts, and only uſe them to ſuch Ends and Purpoſes, to ſuch, and only ſuch, I ſay as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Such Men are grown ſo Worldly Wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Good Men they hate, and them deſpiſe;</l>
                  <l>Such men now act (ſo) craftily,</l>
                  <l>That Good Men (muſt) Meer Beggars dye.</l>
                  <l>But mark the End, what comes at laſt,</l>
                  <l>When Earthly Days are gone and paſt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> doth them tell,</l>
                  <l>Beggars have Heaven, Rich Gluttons Hell.</l>
                  <bibl>[<hi>See</hi> Luke <hi>the 16th Chapter, verſ. 22, 23.</hi>]</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>And now to conclude, I ſay, by means of my thus doing, I am very ſenſible of it, that thereby I have (ſo openly) expoſed my ſelf, that I am now as a Mark to be ſhot at by ſuch Evil-minded Men, as I have here in this Small Treatiſe of mine, in ſome meaſure deſcribed: And therefore I hope, Your moſt <hi>Gratious Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Parliament,</hi> will now be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of my good-will, and to protect me againſt all ſuch Men, as will not only Snarl at me for thus doing, but (Bite) me if they can; and after that, rend me to pieces alſo, if ever it ſhall lie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34674:27"/>in their power ſo to do. But however it be at laſt, yet I hope (God) by his Providence, will ſo far protect me in what I have done, as that he will give them no farther power over me, than to be able to chew the Cud of Envy within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and keep their Malice as Priſoners within their own Breaſt; for the juſt God of Heaven doth know, that by my putting forth of this little Book, that I aim at nothing more than his Glory, and the good of all Men, of all Ranks and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And ſo I conclude this <hi>Firſt Part</hi> of my Work, and farther ſay, (and now) from the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of my Heart, I ſay, God bleſs Your Moſt <hi>Gratious Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Honourable Parliament,</hi> and alſo preſerve our Nation from the Malice of all our Enemies, and all other Calamities whatſoever, that are any ways likely to attend us, is the Prayer of Your <hi>Majeſty's</hi> true Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and alſo the <hi>Honourable Parliament</hi>'s devoted Servant,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Richard Newnam,</hi> of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34674:28"/>
               <head>And now again, I ſay, may it pleaſe Your Moſt <hi>Gratious Majeſty,</hi> and the <hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament,</hi> this <hi>Second Part</hi> of my Diſcourſe, with all humble Submiſſion to Your Greatneſs, theſe I alſo Dedicate, and farther ſay, as followeth.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Great Sirs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AS in my foregoing Diſcourſes, I have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſet forth unto Your Greatneſs, the ſeveral Complaints and Grievances of the Poor, Middle, and Meaneſt ſorts of Your Majeſty's true Loyal Subjects, as they have relation only towards their Bodily Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance: So in theſe my following Diſcourſes, my whole deſign is now, to offer unto Your Goodneſs, the great Complaints and ſore Grievances of all others of Your Majeſty's good and true Loyal Subjects, as they have relation only to the Good and Welfare of their Soul's Health: For the Spirits of all ſuch Good Men, are now moſt ſorely and grievouſly oppreſt, by means of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious growth of <hi>Atheiſm, Errors,</hi> and <hi>evil Examples,</hi> from whence ſpringeth forth all manner of Wickedneſs, Filthineſs, and Lewdneſs, as <hi>Prophanation, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Curſing, Lying, Murthers, Thefts, Sodomies, Buggeries, Inceſts, Drunkenneſs, Gluttonies, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Adulteries, Fornications, Chambering, Wantonneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Looſe Looks, Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Behaviours, mimical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſtures,</hi> and <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene Talks,</hi> in all manner of Communications, in theſe our daily Buſineſſes. For now all chaſt Ears and Eyes are always (and ever) continually anoyed with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34674:28"/>the hearing and ſeeing of ſuch moſt abmoniable, filthy, and frothy Diſcourſes and Actions, ſo as that Good Men cannot hear them without great regret and gaul of Spirit within them.</p>
               <p>And all thoſe before-mentioned Evils, (muſt needs) proceed from ſuch Wants, as I ſhall now forthwith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate unto Your Greatneſs.</p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> of all, I ſay, ſuch Evils, as aforeſaid, did firſt proceed through Mens want of a True Faith in God, and a true Reverence of God.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Through want of Mens having within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, good Hearts, and good Conſciences, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and Men.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> Through want of the due Execution of ſuch good Laws as are already made for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholding of Virtue, and for the Suppreſſing of Vice.</p>
               <p>And now, Great Sirs, according to the beſt of my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, as far as God ſhall be pleaſed to enable me, I ſhall now endeavour to ſet forth all theſe my following Diſcourſes, nakedly, plainly, and innocently, without having in me any manner of Self-Intreſt, Pride, or Vain glory, Envy or Malice, againſt any man or men whatſoever. And the like of this I have already ſaid and done in my other before-mentioned Diſcourſes; for therein I have not (wittingly) or willingly, by any manner of Expreſſion, or Expreſſions, that I know of in the leaſt given any Offence, to any good man, or men, whether Prince, Potentates, or Subjects; but with an innocent open Heart, without any manner of mental Reſervation, with my Pen, I have written to the beſt of my Knowledge, ſo far as I thought it might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for me to do, the very naked Truth, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:34674:29"/>
               <p>And now again, I ſay, as I have in theſe my before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Diſcourſes, always obſerved ſuch Ways and Methods to the beſt of my Endeavours, ſo likewiſe now in theſe my following Diſcourſes, I will endeavour as much as in me lieth, to give no Offence to any man, or men whatſoever, any farther than the ſpeaking of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Truth may give. And therefore, however it may be reſented by ſome me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or all men, yet nevertheleſs what I do now intend to ſpeak, ſhall be the naked Truth, according to the beſt of my Knowledge, and real Belief within me, as God and my own Conſcience can teſtifie for me.</p>
               <p>And now I come to ſet forth to Your Goodneſs, the <hi>Sixth general Head</hi> of my Diſcourſe, which I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to Your Greatneſs in my before-ſaid <hi>Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> to the main of my whole Diſcourſe, and all the before-mentioned Heads therein contain'd, I have already inſiſted on the Particulars of them, and in theſe my before-mention'd and ſeveral Diſcourſes, have therein finiſhed them. And now by God's aſſiſtance, I ſhall endeavour, to the beſt of my power, to ſet forth to Your Greatneſs and Goodneſs, the ſeveral Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of them, before-mentioned, General Heads, which I have not yet diſcourſed upon at large by way of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34674:29"/>
               <head>Part II.</head>
               <p>AND now <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I muſt ſay, ſuch things as I now do intend to diſcourſe of, [are] as I think, all very neceſſary to be thought upon, and are of a far more higher Concernment, than any thing yet, that I have offered in any of my before-going Diſcourſes: And the <hi>firſt</hi> thing that I ſhall offer to the Conſideration of your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is this.</p>
               <p>That notwithſtanding all thoſe hard and dear Times, which of late have been and now are, yet nevertheleſs, all this doth not any way work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hearts of our Prophane and Sturdy Poor, I mean ſuch Poor, as are known by the name of the Mob, or ſturdy Vagabond Poor, of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are (now) become ſo notoriouſly Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as that any one would (almoſt) think that Hell it ſelf, is let looſe amongſt them, and the very (Fiends) thereof inviſible Actors with them, if not really in them. (O!) ſuch things as theſe are ſad to think upon, to ſee, that notwithſtanding all theſe ſeveral Calamities, which ſome of them have known from time to time, and have ſo much Muffered under them; yet all this hath not any way in the leaſt turned them from their Evil Ways, and Prophane Living; for 'tis known that ſome of them that are now thus ſo notoriouſly Wicked, have been under great Wants, from time to time; and yet notwithſtanding all theſe great Wants which they have known, yet they do not now want Hearts to conceive Miſchief, nor Hands to act it, nor
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34674:30"/>Tongues to intice others to do the like.</p>
               <p>But theſe are not the Poor, that I have in my before-mentioned Diſcourſes, ſo much lamented and pittied; and if I may now be but permitted to ſpeak my opinion in this Cauſe, concerning ſuch a Mobb of ſturdy Vagabond Poor, or of ſome other ſuch-like vile and prophane Atheiſtical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, then I will ſay (that I think) there can be no Laws made to ſevere on this ſide Death, to puniſh all ſuch moſt notorious, (wicked) and prophane perſons, as do now even as it were ſeem to ſwarm in this our Nation.</p>
               <p>But here a Query may ariſe, and it may be ſaid, <hi>From whence firſt ſprung all thoſe Vices and Wickedneſſes which do now even as it were reign predominant in this our Land; and that not only amongſt the Mobb, and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond ſturdy Foor, but to much amongſt (almoſt) all Sorts, and all Ranks, and all Degrees, and all Sexes, and (almoſt) all Ages of theſe our People (in this our Nation;) for the very Infant, even as it were, is now become (ſo prophane) as is the Old Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; All thoſe wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Actions, that are now ſo much uſed, and put in practice, both by Men, Women, and Children now amongſt us, firſt came from <hi>Atheiſm Error,</hi> and <hi>Evil Examples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>first</hi> of all I ſay, it firſt came from <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> for when once any one comes to deny God himſelf, what thing is there in the World that ſuch a one will not do next? I ſay, ſuch a one will do any thing whatſoever that his own miſchievous Heart at any time conceives to do, be it what it will: And indeed, much it is to be lamented, to ſee <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm</hi> in this our Age, to become ſuch a vaſt and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34674:30"/>mighty Tree as now it is, that was but a few Years ſince but a young and tender Plant, and but juſt peept up above the Earth, after it had lain ſo long under Ground, and was always trodden down under Foot by all Good Men in former Ages, who would never any way permit it in the leaſt to appear above the Earth: And altho' many of the Antient <hi>Heathen-Philoſophers</hi> in their days, did plant this moſt pernitious Root of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> in moſt places of the World, which took deep root here in <hi>England</hi> amongſt us; for their have always, and ever ſince that time, remained amongſt us ſome ſuch Atheiſtical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who have always, and ever ſince, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the very utmoſt of their powers, from time to time, to cheriſh and nouriſh up the growth of this <hi>Atheiſtical Root,</hi> from which ſpringeth forth that moſt damnable Doctrine, which teacheth ſuch wicked Men to deny all future Beings: But yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, notwithſtanding all that, yet did the good Men of Old, by their good old Ways and Practices, walk in ſuch good old Paths of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which were all both plain and ſmooth, and they were ſo many of them, that then this root of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> had no room to ſpring up in this part of the World; for if at any time then it did but begin to appear, it was then preſently trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den down under Foot, and ſpoiled. But now of late in a few Years, it hath been in this our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very much foſtered up amongſt us; and now at preſent, ſtill is continually fed with that Fat and nouriſhing Soil of all manner of filthy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, Prophaneneſs and Hypocriſie; by means of which this moſt pernicious Root of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> is
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34674:31"/>now grown up, and even in theſe our days is now become a mighty Tree indeed, whoſe very Boughs ſpread both far and wide, and the Leaves thereof do now begin to overſhadow the Glory and Brightneſs of the true <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> &amp; Goſpel of our moſt Bleſſed Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> which is yet by ſome good men's endeavours, (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly) upholden within this our Land, which God of his great Mercy always grant unto us, (and amongſt us) to ſend many more ſuch faithful La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, to prevent the farther growth of this now mighty Tree of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> that ſo at laſt, for want of future nouriſhment, it may at laſt (pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by the root) and ſo at laſt dye evelaſtingly away, is my Prayer.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly,</hi> I ſay, from this pernitious Root of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> ſprings forth Errors: For no ſooner can a Traveller be out of his right way, but he muſt (inevitably) be in a wrong Path, that will lead him aſide, or backwards, ſo that by means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it may be a long time before he will be able to reach to his Journeys-end. Again, I ſay, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophers do hold this for a Maxim, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is no Vacuum in the Globe of the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> World; (which if ſo) then comparatively I may ſay, that in the whole Body of <hi>Divinity,</hi> ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can be no Vacuum, but it muſt be full of Truth or Truth mixt with Error. Again, I ſay, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> likely a thing it is, that if Truth in any Cauſe Matter, or Things whatſoever, fly from, or give ground to Error, then conſequently Errors wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtep into Truth's Ground, and ſo poſſeſs Truth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place; which things of late Years, by ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, hath been found to true: For through th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34674:31"/>Erroneous Lives of ſome Men, that do profeſs themſelves to be true <hi>Church of England</hi> Men, (Truth) by means thereof, hath of late Years been a great Sufferer, (whilſt) Errors in the mean time hath gained great Applauſes amongſt ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le and weak Ones. And no wonder is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> made of it, if we do but conſider how man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there be, that do profeſs themſelves to be of, and for, and belonging to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that can ſay no more in the defence of their Faith, than to ſay, <hi>Here is a Health to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>with confuſion to all them that are of any other Opinion.</hi> But ſuch Expreſſions and Sayings are not only fooliſh and bruitiſh, but they are very uncharitable alſo; and the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> teacheth ſuch Men (as ſo ſay) better Principles; for it teacheth all Men to have Charity for all Perſons, and all ſorts of People, as well for ſuch (as are not of that Faith) as for thoſe that are within the Pale of that Church: And therefore, I ſay, great pity it is, and much to be lamented, and I my ſelf cannot otherwiſe but be much troubled for it, to ſee, and hear, ſuch (a) moſt worthy, honourable, excellent, (and) authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Religion, ſo much ſlighted, undervalued, and deſpiſed, as now our moſt honourable <hi>Church of England</hi> is, by many poor, ſimple, (and weak Creatures) who through want of Right Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſtumble at Truth, in the very plain Ways and Paths of Righteouſneſs it ſelf; and that only becauſe ſome of the Paſtors of our Church, are now become (fooliſh) bruitiſh, and very looſe Livers, throughout their whole Lives and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations: But the greater is the ſhame to all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34674:32"/>ſuch of them as ſo do, and ſo live; and a great Account one Day for it they muſt all give. (And now) with all my Heart I could wiſh, that all ſuch Evil Members were caſt out of our Church, for they do meerly thereby [Eclipſe] the very Glory of our Religion; and ſuch Men cannot be otherwiſe but like great Stumbling-blocks, which ſtill lie in the very middle way of our Church-Paths, which leads towards our ſeveral Sanctuaries, and thereby keep back many Simple Ones from going to hear God's Word truly preach'd, by other worthy Members of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe Lives and Converſations, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways adorned their Preaching: But yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, notwithſtanding all this (yet) ſuch are the weak Capacities of many People, that when they ſee ſuch ſtumbling-Blocks lie in the way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and juſt in the very Church-Path it ſelf, (then) rather than they will ſtep over them, or endeavour to avoid them, by their going onward by either of the ſides of them, (they) will rather go back again, (or) turn in, to ſome other unknown ways, wherein it may be at laſt, they many of them do ſtumble indeed, and many times thereby fall in Head-long into that moſt dangerous Gulf of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it ſelf: And ſuch things as theſe, I my ſelf do much lament them, as I my ſelf am one of that Faith, which is of, and belonging to that Church, known by the Name of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> from which Faith I hope I ſhall never waver.</p>
               <p>But again, it may be ſaid, <hi>What, are there none that do live in Lewdneſs, and lead wicked prophane Lives, but ſuch Men as are called by the Name of Church of</hi> England <hi>Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34674:32"/>
               <p>To this I Anſwer; There be ſome of all Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Profeſſions, that are altogether ſo vile, and as filthy in their Lives and Converſations, as any Church-men whatſoever, (only) they have a way of carrying it off more privately to the World; for what they do, is more ſecretly, and more Hypocritically; ſo that I cannot decide the matter, (ſo) as to ſay which is the worſt of them, (both of them) and all of them, are all to bad; and I heartily wiſh, that they may all and every one of them amend, and turn from their evil ways, (as I my ſelf) ſhall endeavour to amend my own evil ways; for I acknowledge my ſelf to be a great Sinner</p>
               <p>And now I ſay to you my Native Country-men, of our Town of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> ſpare me not, but either exclaim againſt me (or reprove me) in or for any thing that is Evil, that you either know (in me) or of me, or againſt me; and if it be true, that you lay to my Charge, I will patiently bare your Reproof, and endeavour to amend what is in me amiſs, to the beſt of my power; and for what is wanting in my ſelf, to be enabled ſo to do, I ſhall deſire God to aſſiſt me, ſo as that I may be the better able to eſchew all manner of Evil, and follow nothing but what is Good: And the ſame Reſolution (in every thing) I adviſe all and every of you, and all other Perſons whatſoever, that hope to be ſaved in and through the Love of God, and the Merits of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt) you all of you, and every of you ought to take; which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution ſo taken, and ſo put in Practice, then we ſhall all of us (at laſt) reap the benefit of it, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:34674:33"/>
               <p>But again, ſomething more I muſt ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Errors,</hi> and <hi>Erroneous Livers,</hi> and that is this; I ſay, take this for certain, that amongſt all our Opinions, Sects, and Religions, their are ſome Errors: For their is but One true God, but One true Religion, but One true Faith, and but One true Way, to ſerve this true God. (Then) how can ſo many Ways as we profeſs, in and about matters of Religion, be all and every of them true? [This] to the Eye of Senſe and Reaſon cannot be, (nor to the Eye of Faith either, can it ſo appear to be.) And therefore I muſt ſay again, [Errors] are crept in amongſt us, and we do even as it were cheriſh them in our Boſoms, only to gratifie our Pride, [or] Vain-glory, [or] Self-Intereſt, or to ſhew our Natural Parts: And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of rooting out of this thing called <hi>Error,</hi> many do plainly ſhew to the World, that they aim at nothing more than what I have but juſt now ſaid; for how many Volumes have ſome Men writ to reclaim <hi>Errors?</hi> and when they have all done, by their [Works] it hath then plainly appeared, to the Wiſeſt and moſt Judicious Men of our Age, that what they have ſo much cavilled about, hath been at laſt (more) about indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Words, than matter tending to the Salvation of Souls: And at laſt, when they have all done, they have (then) committed more Errors in their ſeveral Diſputations, than ever they amended with all their Epiſtles, (Writings) or large Volumes. And moreover, I muſt ſay, that ſome Men, by ſuch Epiſtles, Writings, and Volumes, have thereby laid open a wide [and broad Path] only fit to lead poor weak capacitated Souls to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34674:33"/>deſtruction, for thereby they have meerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the plain honeſt Underſtandings of many People, who have read all over their Cavilling Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, and then at laſt for want of a right Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them, have ſaid, <hi>We ſee how all thoſe Scepticks, or Sectaries, differ in all their Points about matters of Religion, and ſome of them lead as looſe Lives as any other People whatſoever; and therefore we will believe in none of them.</hi> And ſo conſequently em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all manner of Evil, and at laſt, believe in the Doctrine of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it ſelf, and in their Hearts then ſay, if not with their Mouths, <hi>That there is no God to call them to Account;</hi> for ſay they, (theſe ſimple poor weak ones) <hi>If ſuch Men, of all Religions, did agree in their Opinions about God, and the ways of Godlineſs, we ſhould then think there were [a God] to puniſhus, for our Evil Doings: But we do ſee (they do not agree) in ſuch things: And beſides all this</hi> (ſay they) <hi>in and by their Looſe and Erroneous Livings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis plainly ſeen that they themſelves [do not believe] in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat God which they teach us to believe in:</hi> For then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay thoſe ſimple ones, <hi>If ſuch Men did really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieve in God, as they profeſs they do, then they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>read the thoughts of offending that God: Or if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id in themſelves really believe, that there is ſuch an Everlaſting Burning of Hell-Fire [prepared] for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch Men as live looſely and carleſly, then (certainly) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one of them would ever live (in known Sins) nor ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve ſuch wicked and debaucht Lives as many of them do, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mongſt all ſorts of Profeſſors.</hi> And then they, thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oor weak ſimple Souls ſay again, <hi>[Religion] that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt needs be but a meer Bug-Bear, to keep the vulgar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ort of People in awe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:34674:34"/>
               <p>And therefore I muſt ſay again, that I think, it would be much the better way, for all ſuch Men, as do ſpend (ſo) much time, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, and many other unneceſſary Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, [now] to ſpend the remaining part of their moſt) pretious time, in Preaching down Sin and Wickedneſs, and in teaching their ſeveral Flocks, the ways of Virtuous Living, [and alſo] by their future Lives and Converſations, [always] from time to time, endeavour to the utmoſt of their power, to adorn that Doctrine, which they preach to others, with their own Vertuous Living, and in all their ſeveral doings, be always ſtriving to diſcharge their Conſciences in their ſeveral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, both towards God and Man. And then all ſuch Errors as are now crept in amongſt us, (with many other Evils) will vaniſh, and dye away for want of future Nouriſhment.</p>
               <p>But ſuch Complaints as theſe [made] by ſo mean a Creature as I am, may be but little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded: And therefore I will now offer unto you <hi>Solomon</hi>'s own Words for it, which I think hath ſome relation to theſe Diſcourſes of mine, (here in before-mentioned) read <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.12, 13, 14 it is there ſaid, <hi>And further by theſe my Son, be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, of making many Books there is no end; and much Study is a wearineſs of the Fleſh.</hi> Let us hear the Concluſion of the whole mater, <hi>Fear God, and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole Duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Man; for God ſhall bring every work [in to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment] with every ſecret thing, whether it be good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> whether it be evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus I have endeavoured to ſet forth unto you, how that from <hi>Atheiſm</hi> comes Errors; and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34674:34"/>alſo, that looſe Living doth always ſtill enlarge the Territories of <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> And then, thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> muſt ſpring forth that dangerous, and moſt malignant Root, called Evil Examples; and this is the next thing that I ſhall now inſiſt upon.</p>
               <p>And now I ſay, that <hi>Evil Examples</hi> may fitly be compared to a Wilderneſs-like Country, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath in it more Woods and Forreſts, than good Paſture-Ground, or Tillage-Land; but yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſame Wilderneſs-like Ground, wherein theſe Woods and Trees grow in, if once they be throughly rooted out, with all the reſt of the Bryars and Thorns, that grow amongſt them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen that ſame Wilderneſs-like Ground in time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay be as fit for good Paſturage, or Tillage-Land, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s any other whatſoever. But then this muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one by the induſtry of good Husbandmen, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>therwiſe in time, ſuch Woods and Forreſts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ether with ſuch Bryars and Thorns, which grow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mongſt them, may at laſt over-run and ſpoil that Ground next thereto belonging, which is now fit or good Paſturage, or good Tillage-Land: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his I ſpeak Metaphorically.</p>
               <p>But now more really and plainly concerning <hi>Evil Examples,</hi> I ſay, too many of them there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow in this our Engliſh Nation, for they ſwarm, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re now very numerous, (nay) almoſt beyond number, or at leaſt, ſo Beaſt-like odious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hane, that no Man, that is a good Chriſtian, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut a moral honeſt ſober Man, but muſt be afraid) or aſhamed to name them, [except] meet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceſſity, upon ſome extraordinary occaſions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ompel him ſo to do.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:34674:35"/>
               <p>But ſo it is, that they now reign predominant in this our Nation, to that height and degree, ſo as that there are ſome of all Ranks, Degrees, Sexes, Ages, Profeſſions, and Callings, corrupted by them ſome way or other, more or leſs: For inſtead of Virtue and Chaſtity, is uſed Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Wantonneſs: And inſtead of Hoſpitality and Charity, is uſed Fraud and Oppreſſion: And inſtead of Faſting and Temperance, is uſed Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and Drukenneſs. And inſtead of Meekneſs with true Religion, is uſed Pride and Hypocriſie: And inſtead of Prayers and Supplications, is uſed Curſings and Swearings: And inſtead of ſaying, <hi>God ſave us,</hi> 'tis now (almoſt) a general ſaying, <hi>God D—m-us:</hi> And inſtead of ſaying, <hi>Chriſt have Mercy upon us,</hi> 'tis now a general ſaying, <hi>The D—vil confound us.</hi> O! what moſt horrid Sins are theſe! for Men to call on him that made them, to damn them; and alſo to call for the Devil to confound them, that is always ſeeking about like a Roaring Lyon to devour them, and would ſoon make them his Prey, if God out of his moſt bountiful Mercy towards poor frail Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, did not confine him within his Bounds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond which he cannot go. But however, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding God's great mercy towards all men, yet it will be the greteſt Prudence in every one of us, to have great care within our ſelves, how we do offend this great God, that in the firſt place created us, and ſtil hither to hath preſerved us, leſt we ſhould at laſt provoke him to great anger. O! how would ſuch prophane Wretches look, if God ſhould in the very Moment of Time, given unto ſuch Men, what they in their outragious Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34674:35"/>call for. Oh! think upon theſe things, all ye Black mouth'd Swearers and Curſers, that do by this moſt abominable way of Swearing, &amp; Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thus prophane God, and would your own Souls: O! you that do ſo vehemently belch forth from, your bottomleſs Pits within you, ſuch Burning Oaths as if the very Sulphrous Matter of <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf were in a Flame within your own Breaſts. O! ſuch Wickedneſs as theſe alone, are enought to pull down God's Vengeance upon us: But more-eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when all the other of thoſe our Accomplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sins and Wickedneſſes, of our whole Nation are conjoin'd altogether, with thoſe moſt abominable Oaths and Curſings, what then can we expect but the Viols of God's wrath, at laſt to be poured down upon us. Except by our true Repentance and Amendment of Life, we endeavour to prevent them; By puting a ſpeedy ſtop to theſe our moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Crimes, which Daily and Hourly we commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, (otherwiſe) 'tis much to be doubted, that our Land (at laſt) may become a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs indeed.</p>
               <p>But again, it may be ſaid, <hi>There are good and wholſome Laws made to prevent all manner of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; And what can there be more done to prevent ſuch evills, than there is done already?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this I anſwer; There are good and who;l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws already made, and ſufficient enough to puniſh all manner of Vices; but there are now but few Complainers againſt Vices, and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for ſome are afraid to Complain, becauſe (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) for ſo doing they doubt thereby, they ſhall reap to themſelves nothing but evil-will and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain. And then others there are, that areas much
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34674:36"/>aſhamed to complain; and ſo by means of ſome ſuch, and ſuch other like things, theſe good and wholſome Laws are not put in due Execution, as they ought to be. But why ſuch things as theſe are, ſhould be ſo, I cannot tell, (except) it be, becauſe there is a general Corruption, crept into the Natures of moſt Men, which makes the Wicked ſo concientious towards the Ungodly; or if they do accuſe one the other, they will not ſtand the Tryal of it, but juſt like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when they brought the Woman taken in Adultry, before our Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and then ſaid to him, <hi>Moſes in the Law, commanded us that ſuch ſhould be Stoned; But what ſayeſt thou?</hi> The Chriſt anſwered them, <hi>He that is without Sin, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, let him firſt caſt a Stone at her;</hi> Which neither of they (the ſaid <hi>Scibes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi>) did do; becauſe every one of them (was convicted in his own Conſcience) to be as great a Sinner, as the Woman whom they had then taken in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and ſo their own Guilt made them at laſt, to leave her without proſecuting any further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her; and like guilty offenders, ſneakt all away, and left the Adulterous Woman all alone; But when Chriſt obſerved that, he ſaid unto her, <hi>Woman, where are thoſe thine accuſers; hath no Man condemned thee? She ſaid, No man, Lord. And Jeſus ſaid unto her, Neither do I condemn thee: go and Sin no more.</hi> See in the 8th Chapter of Saint <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, beginning at the 3 <hi>d.</hi> verſe, and ſo on ward to the 12th verſe.</p>
               <p>And now to apply theſe things to our ſelves, I think I may without giving offence to any one, (ſay) that it would be beſt of all, for all ſorts of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34674:36"/>Men, that know themſelves to be guilty of any manner of Crimes, or other Wickedneſes whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, firſt of all earneſtly to ſeek God in Prayer, and to beg of him his aſſiſtance, that he now will be pleas'd to give them ſuch hearts, as may be fit for true Repentance, and then alſo endeavour to the utmoſt of their power, true amendment of Life, and then undoubtedly, all ſuch of us as are now aſhamed to accuſe on the other, might at laſt be forgiven, or at leaſt excuſed, as the Woman taken in Adultry was, provided on ſuch (conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) that wel all of us, would fully reſolve ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to commit any ſuch moſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nous Crimes or other Wickedneſſes any more; which if we could but ſo do, then we might at laſt, all of us, for ſo doing, in and through the Merits of our moſt bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Law of God, and then we ſhould have no need to trouble, or fear the Laws of Men.</p>
               <p>But again, I ſay evil Examples have been ſo many of them in this our Age, that their(pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,) in number, are now become (almoſt) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, for they have ſwarmed many a time [o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,] and over again, and now many (Colonies) of them are ſent abroad, to inhabit our Land all over, in every Creek and Corner of it; (O) what is it, that Example may not do, either in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to what is Good, or to that which is Evil; for it is not obſerved, throughout the whole courſe of Nature, that every thing after his kind, endeavours to produce it's like: Doth not Love beget Love? And do not Courteſies require Kindneſs? (or on the Contrary) doth not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34674:37"/>beget Hatred? and do not wronged Perſons, often times ſeek Revenge? And then, from one quarrel another doth ſtill ariſe, untill a World (almoſt) are all by the Ears, fallen out with one and the other; and that only by ſuch means, as when like to like doth agree, and join with each party, and that accordingly as by their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture within them (they are either inclin'd) to Love or Hate. And is it not further obſerved, that the Sober, and true Religious, and honeſt Plain-hearted Man, delights in the company of ſuch a one as he knows himſelf to be! Yes, if he can tell where to find him out, he will have his company. But farther, it is not alſo obſerv'd, and by experience found, that <hi>Drunkards, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Whoremongers, Thieves, Lyars,</hi> ſecret <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners,</hi> and Clandeſtine <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and all other ſorts of diſſembling Hypocrites whatſoever, do na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſire each others company, and do often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Flock together! And they need not ſeek very far for Company, for there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them now in this our Age, as that they crowd together, almoſt as thick as Earthly Atoms in the Air, which cannot well be ſeen, but only when the Sun ſhineth in through the little Holes or Chinks of a Door, that encloſeth a dark Room. And indeed and in truth, I may very well now ſay, that ſuch evil Men as aforeſaid, do always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be in dark Rooms, and they do [not] love Light, nor do they any way deſire, that the Son of Righteouſneſs ſhould ever ſhine into their Rooms amongſt them; for then they know that all their black Deeds will be as plainly ſeen by all men, as Earthly Atoms are ſeen in a dark
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34674:37"/>Room, by the Power and Strength of the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams, when they are ſo contracted together, and ſent through ſuch little Holes, Chinks, or Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of ſuch a Door, as it is before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>Again I ſay, Evil Examples are very malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in their own Natures, and that many ways, as by woful experience it hath been oftentimes found, for when the Father is a common Drunkard, the Son often-times doth prove to be the like; and indeed, according to the courſe of Nature, it is not much to be admired at, for Cuſtom is a ſecond Nature, and ſome men do by Cuſtom, bring up their Children ſo to do, as they love to do themſelves; for when the Son goes to call his Drunken Father home from the Ale-houſe, or Tavern, he will then make his Child drink ſeveral times (perhaps) much againſt his Stomach, and then when the Lads ſquemiſh Stomach loathes the taking in of ſo much Liquor, then the drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Father ſaith, <hi>(How) Sarrah, can't you drink? (what) you dont know what's good for your ſelf; Come drink it all up Boy, and I'll make you love good Liquor as well as my ſelf; for I find it to be a great Comfort to my Heart.</hi> And this way the Drunkard in time, makes his Son to become as common a Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard as himſelf; But again, ſometimes if ſo comes to paſs, that the Son of a Debauch Laſcivious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the days of his Infancy, makes ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of his Father's lewd Actions, tho' at that time (perhaps) for want of Reaſon, he is not capable to think it to be in his Father, any way Immodeſt, or Evil; But then after that, when he the Son comes to ſee more Years in the World, and is then ſomewhat more Ripened in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34674:38"/>Age, and his own wanton deſires begin to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play themſelves, within his own Breſt. Then (perhaps) he begins to recal to mind, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Actions that he had oftentimes ſeen, by his Laſcivious Father, and then thinks he within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Why may not I my ſelf do the like?</hi> And thus through want of good Examples, he is prone to all manner of Evil, and then he the Son, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lets looſe the Reins of his Will, to run into all manner of Wickedneſs. And thus ſuch Evil Examples, are oftentimes the chief ſecondary Cauſes, that have corrupted ſo many Thouſands, of our brave Vigorous Young Men, ſo as that thereby, at laſt many of them have paid the Debt which they owed to Nature, with their untime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deaths, and inſtead of a Chriſtian Burial in the Church-yard, they have been thrown into a moſt ſhameful Grave, under the Gallows.</p>
               <p>Again, the ſame may be ſaid concerning Mothers and Daughters, for if the Mother, throughout her whole Life and Converſation, be Vitiouſly given to all manner of Lewdneſs, and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Then 'tis a rare thing, to ſee the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch a Woman truly Vertuous; tho' ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, now and than, 'tis known, that Wicked Parents have had good Children, and good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, have had Wicked Children, but much more often 'tis known, that good Education and good Examples, hath often times changed the corrupt Natures of many, ſo as that by mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereof, they at laſt have become tollerably good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that otherwiſe would have been moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Evil, and by this alſo, may be ſeen, what Effect Good or Evil Examples, can produce. The
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34674:38"/>like alſo, concerning Good and Evil Examples, may be ſaid between Maſters and Servants, for if the Maſter be a common Swearer, 'tis much if the Servant is not alſo tempted to break out now and than with an Oath, altho' originally he was otherwiſe taught by his Honeſt Parents, for did not good <hi>Joſeph</hi> learn to Swear by the Life of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> after he had been but a little while in the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Court, and it may be, he had heard many of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> oftentimes ſo to ſwear; ſee <hi>Geneſis</hi> the 24th Chapter, verſe 15.</p>
               <p>But farther, concerning Evil Examples, I muſt ſay the greateſt danger of them all, is when they are found in Magiſtrates, and Miniſters, for they hereby do not only (corrupt) ſingle Perſons, or peculiar Families, but whole Cities, Towns, and Villages.</p>
               <p>But again, The next thing, that will come in this my way of Diſcourſe, I think will be to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſet forth the ſad and direful effects, of ſuch Evil Examples. And now I farther ſay, the Evil Examples that have been to frequently ſhewn in this our Age, by almoſt all ſorts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of all Sexs, and Ages, have been the only ſecondary Cauſes, that hath infuſed into our Hearts; this now general reigning Corruption, by means of which (many ways) we have high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended God. And therefore I now (believe) that the Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth, now forth with doth expect from every one of us, a true and hearty Repentance, with the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of our Lives, and Reſtitution made to thoſe whom we have any way wronged, or otherwiſe we may for ought I know, (to ſoon)
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34674:39"/>feel the weight of God's Wrath powered down upon us, but yet nevertheleſs, by experience it hath been found, that before the Almighty God, hath pouered down the Viols of his Wrath upon the Heads of the moſt Wicked, and vileſt Sinners, [he] out of his great Mercy, (hath hitherto) always given them warning before hand, by the Signs and Tokens of his diſpleaſure, made manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them both in Heaven and on Earth. And if I miſtake not, I think the manifeſtation of ſuch Tokens, of God's diſpleaſure againſt a Nation (have) or might, of late Years been plainly ſeen in <hi>England:</hi> But however, when God is diſpleaſed with any Nation and People, that it is then his Good will and Pleaſure, to give Warnings before he ſtrikes, is plainly to be made manifeſt; and to prove this, I need not uſe many Arguments, for both Divine and Moral Hiſtories are full of ſuch Preſidents:</p>
               <p>And the <hi>firſt</hi> of them that I ſhall offer to you, for the proof hereof, ſhall be that of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> in his Moral Hiſtory, concerning the City of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> who, if I miſtake not, therein ſaith, That a <hi>Flaming Sword</hi> for a conſiderable time appeared over that City, before the Deſtruction of it: And if the Impenitent <hi>Jews</hi> had then at the ſight thereof, truly Repented, who can tell but God might have had Mercy upon them. But they did not Repent, and therefore at laſt they felt the ſad Effects of it.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly,</hi> Divine Hiſtory ſaith, That the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Old World cauſed the Flood to be brought upon them; and yet God in his Mercy then gave them One Hundred and Twenty Years
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34674:39"/>to Repent, as you may read in the 6th Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> verſ. 3. But they of the Old World in all that time, did not Repent; and therefore at laſt they were all drowned in the Flood; ſee in 7th Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> verſ. 12.</p>
               <p>Again, I ſay, <hi>Nineveh</hi> was a great City, and the People thereof very Wicked; ſee <hi>Jonah,</hi> chap. 1. ver. 2. For their Wickedneſs was grown to that prodigious height, that it aſcended up to Heaven before the Lord, and therefore God pronounc'd his Judgments againſt them, by the Mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jonah:</hi> But as ſoon as <hi>Jonah</hi> had Preach'd the Word of the Lord unto them, and told them, <hi>Yet forty Days, and</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</hi> Then they preſently Believed, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented from the higheſt to the loweſt of them; and therefore God ſhewed them Mercy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of the Evil that he had ſaid (he would do unto them;) ſee in <hi>Jonah,</hi> chap. 3. from the firſt verſe to the end of that Chapter.</p>
               <p>And thus we may ſee, that God doth firſt of all ſhew himſelf a God of Mercy, before he doth ſhew himſelf to be the God of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>And therefore I may now (juſtly) and truly ſay, without giving offence to any Man, that God hath been, and ſtill is, very Merciful to us here in <hi>England,</hi> (and that) in his forbearing of us, in all theſe our Infirmities, with great Patience: For is not our Land now become a very ſinful Nation? (O) what Wickedneſs is their in the whole World, that is not (now) acted, done, and committed here in <hi>England</hi> amongſt us; (for now) in this [our] Age, (home) to this very day, do not we continually (wallow) in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34674:40"/>prophane, wicked, foul, filthy, ſhameful Sins of <hi>Sabbath-breaking, Hypocriſie, Pride, Whoredoms, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy, Murthers, Blaſphemy, Swearing, Curſing, Flattering, Lying, Frauds, Perjuries, Thieving, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Dealing, Covetouſneſs, Self-intreſt,</hi> with all maner of Undermining, Falſhood, and with Hearts full of ſecret Miſchief, ſtriving by all manner of falſe ways, (Clandeſtinely) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and undermine our fellow Creatures; and (yet) at the ſame time, with a <hi>Judas</hi>-like Kiſs, or Counterfeit Smile, profeſs themſelves real Friends [to him] or them [whom he or they] at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time, intend to deceive. (O!) what greater Wickedneſs than theſe can there be in the whole World? And ſuch Wickedneſs, as theſe, do not only continue amongſt us, but [now] they do ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabound abundantly, beyond meaſure, all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> over.</p>
               <p>And therefore (I ſay) both from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Scripture,</hi> rationally and divinely, we may all of us [think] our ſelves to be as great Sinners, as any were in the Old World, or in any other Nation, ever ſince the World began, who have been deſtroyed for their Sins: And therefore ['tis now] high time for us all to Repent, and Amend our Lives, for who can tell what may follow theſe our moſt great and grievous Sins? And 'tis to be queſtioned, whether our Sins may deſerve that Mercy from God, which the <hi>Ninehvite</hi>'s then received from him; for they, the <hi>Ninehvite's,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately Repented at the Preaching of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jonah,</hi> as you may read it in the 12th Chap. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> verſ. 41. But for our ſelves, 'tis much to be feared, that our Impenitent Hearts, are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34674:40"/>now much like the Hearts of the old <hi>Jews,</hi> who were too much hardened to repent; which if ſo, who can tell, how ſoon we may feel the ſevere Judgments of God amongſt us; for we are as great Sinners as any of they were; look in the 13th Chapter of Saint <hi>Luke's</hi> Goſpel, the 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5th verſes, and there you will find, that when ſome told Chriſt what great Sinners the <hi>Galileans</hi> were; Jeſus anſwered them, <hi>Suppoſe ye that theſe</hi> Galileans <hi>were ſinners above all the</hi> Galileans? <hi>I tell you Nay: But except ye repent, ye ſhall all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh. Or thoſe eighteen, upon whom the Tower in</hi> Siloam <hi>fell, and ſlew them, think ye they were Sinners above all men that dwelt in</hi> Jeruſalem? <hi>I tell you, Nay: But except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> And thus we ſee, the <hi>Jews</hi> had warning from Chriſt himſelf, and yet they did not Repent. And now are not we in <hi>England</hi> warned to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? and that not only by Signs and Tokens from Heaven and Earth, but by the Holy Bible, the written Word of God, wherein we may ſee by all the Commandments of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, and by all the ſayings of the Prophets, and the Preachings of the Apoſtles, that all ſuch horrid Sins as we now daily commit, and live in them, are moſt abominable in the Eyes of the Almighty God: And therefore, it is now high time for every one of us, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to Repent, and turn us, every one of us, from our Evil Ways. And though we have not (now) amongſt us, in theſe our days (perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) the Prophets, and Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſtles, to teach us and reprove us, yet we have to this very day, left unto us, by divine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34674:41"/>Records, for our Doctrine, for our Inſtructions, and for our Reproof, all their Holy Sayings, and Preachings. And beſides all this, we cannot to this very day, pretend to make any excuſe for it, that we have not ſufficient warning given us, to Repent us of all our Evil Doings; for God be thanked for it, ſtill to this very day, there are not wanting in our <hi>Church of England,</hi> many good, devout, and moſt eminent Preachers, that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſhew themſelves like good Paſtors, and are faithful Shepherds over their Flocks; and every <hi>Sabbath-day,</hi> do by their moſt powerful and preſſing Arguments, uſe their utmoſt endeavours to perſwade Sinners, and to reclaim them from all their Evil Ways, exhorting them to true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and Amendment of Life; and alſo, to endeavour always to live in Obedience to all the Laws of God, and all the Commandments and Sayings of our bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: And then for the better performance of it, they are not wanting, to offer up their moſt devout Prayers (to Almighty God) for his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to remain upon them. Theſe Paſtors, and only ſuch good Paſtors as theſe are (are now) the only true <hi>Moſes</hi>'s, &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi>'s that are now left on the Earth, to ſtand in the Gaps, and Ways, in which deſtruction cometh; and there do lift up their moſt devout Hearts and Hands, and interceed unto the Lord for us. And thus by their Prayers, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Prayers of all other true devout <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> God's moſt ſevere <hi>Judgments,</hi> (have hither<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to) been ſtopt from falling down upon us: But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thoſe Signs, and Tokens, and Warnings (if at
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34674:41"/>laſt) we will be like the Impenitent <hi>Jews,</hi> and will not repent us of our Evil Ways, then our Puniſhments will be only from our ſelves: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to prevent all ſuch Evils, let us now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th repent us from the very bottom of our H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, as the <hi>Ninevite</hi>'s did (and alſo) that we may be the better, enabled ſo to do, let us now forthwith (firſt of all,) every one of us look into our own particular Hearts, and ſee what is there amiſs, and amend it: And after that, to the very utmoſt of our power, (evermore) ſhun all manner of Evils, and then we may (yet) hope for Mercy at God's Hands; but otherwiſe, no leſs can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him, but his moſt ſevere Judgments to be poured down upon us.</p>
               <p>And now <hi>Seventhly,</hi> I ſay, from the Holy Bible, which I believe to be the written Word of God, and from the Experience of my own Actions; as alſo from the obſervation and experience of many other Men's actions, that I have known, or have heard of, from the Mouths of credible Perſons, I have grounded all theſe my former Diſcourſes; from which Fountain has flown all that I have ſaid, wherein I have endeavoured to ſet forth the ſeveral wicked Actions, of almoſt all People, here within this out Land or Nation: And with theſe our Actions [God] is not well pleaſed, as doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the ſeveral Signs and Tokens of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, which may be ſeen plainly, if we look no farther than [this] how every Year, (Year) after Year, now of late, one part or other of our Land, hath failed of having plentiful Crops of Corn, much more than uſually it hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34674:42"/>in ſome Years paſt, before theſe now late ſcanty Years for formerly I have known for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years together, we have had plentiful Crops, Year after Year: But it is much to be doubted, that, that time of fulneſs of Bread, made us fat, as that we thereby only grew Wanton and Laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civious, and ſo conſequently have run into all manner of Evils: But now, it ſeems to appear to [me] that God hath of late been pleaſed to try us with a Scanty, thereby to ſee how every one of us would behave our ſelves under it; and it may be alſo, to ſee whether the Poor would thereby become truly Penitent; as alſo, to ſee whether the Rich would be Charitable: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it appears ſo to [me] both by the Eyes of Reaſon and Faith, as if God of late Years had ſo ordered things to be, (only) to try us in and by theſe Ways and Manners of dealing with us: For by obſervation of late Years, it hath been found, through the moſt part of our Land, that if in one part of our Land, their hath been an indifferent plenty (then) for that other places have ſo much failed. And then again, theſe Places of our Land, that have failed that one Year, (have had indifferent Plenty the next Year (following) that Year of ſcanty. [Or thus] again I ſay, they that have had a plentiful Crop of Corn, (when others) have had the ſame (Year) but a ſcanty Crop; then the next (Year) following, they that have had the Year before (a ſcanty crop) have had then their plentiful Crop: And then they that had the Year before their (plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Crop) have had their ſcanty Crop for it.— But to explain it more ſhort, take it thus; I ſay
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34674:42"/>(generally) of late Years, by experience it hath been found, (he) that had a plentiful Crop of Corn (the one year) had a ſcanty Crop for it the next Year following. So that upon the whole of the matter, it doth appear to me, by Reaſon, as well as by Faith (to believe) that the [Almighty] hath of late, ſo meaſured out all his Bleſſings, only to try the Hearts of Men, that it might be ſeen by their Actions what their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards God and Men would be, and how far their Charity would extend to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. [But again,] I have obſerved (alſo) that notwithſtanding the Almighty's diſpleaſure with us, yet in the general, we have had enough, every Year throughout our Land, one where with the other, of all ſorts of Grain, and of all others ſorts of Proviſions; but Men have not diſtributed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in our Nation, as God would have had it done, for inſtead of Charity to their Neighbours, they have made a meer Prey of them, and have alſo ſought out wicked Inventions, meerly to grind the Poor even as it were to duſt: And therefore it is that I doubt, that for thoſe things God hath yet a Controverſie to be diſputed with ſuch men as have by ſeveral ways and means, before mentioned, thus oppreſſed the Poor and Needy; and that do put their truſt more in their god <hi>(Mammon)</hi> than they do in the Great God of Heaven: But let ſuch Men know, that, that God, that made them to that end and purpoſe, to do good in their Generation, can deſtroy them for their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a moment; read the whole Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Obadiah,</hi> but more particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe following Verſes of that Chapter,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34674:43"/>which I have quoted at large, in the 3d and 4th Verſes thereof, 'tis ſaid, <hi>The pride of thine Heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwelleſt in the clifts of the rock, whoſe habitation is high, that ſaith in his heart, Who ſhall bring me down to the ground? Though thou exalt thy ſelf as the Eagle, and though thou ſet thy Neſt among the Stars, thence will I bring thee down, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And in the 6th, 7th and 8th Verſes 'tis ſaid, <hi>How are the things of</hi> Eſau <hi>ſearched out? How are his hid things ſought up? All the Men of thy Confederacy have brought thee even to the Border? the men that were at peace with thee, have deceived thee, and prevailed againſt thee; they that eat thy Bread, have laid a Wound under thee; there is none un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in them. Shall I not in that Day, ſaith the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd, even deſtroy the Wiſe Men out of</hi> Edom, <hi>and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding out of the Mount of</hi> Eſau? And in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 10th V rſs, 'tis ſaid, <hi>For thy violence againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ther</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſhame ſhall cover thee, and thou ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be cut off forever.</hi> And alſo, in the 15th Verſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>For the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd is near upon all the Heathen; as thou h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt done, it ſhall be done unto thee; thy Reward ſhall return upon thine own Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now again, I ſay, if any of our Star-gazers, who are called by the Name of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> ſhall read theſe my Diſcourſes, they will ſay of me, <hi>He hath written like a Fool;</hi> for we know that all ſuch diſorderly ſeaſons, as have been of late Years, comes from no other Cauſes, than from the natural Influences of the Heavenly Bodies, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own due Courſes, as they were by God himſelf firſt ordained, for them to continue in, without any alteration (only) as to Time, and Motion, they vary in their ſeveral Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34674:43"/>and ſo then conſequently, it muſt follow, that from time, to time, the Seven wandring Planets, muſt be every Year, Year after Year, always variouſly placed, in their ſeveral Poſitions, and as variable in their Conjunctions, or Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, or Squares: And then, as they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, more or leſs, in theſe their ſeveral Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to all thoſe other innumerable company of Fixed Stars, (ſo) accordingly) they do always beſtow (their ſeveral Influences) upon the Earth; or to expreſs my ſelf more plain (I ſay) that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, as all the Heavenly Bodies, (are in their ſeveral Poſitions, and Courſes, either Benignally, or Malignally inclined towards us, even ſo the Seaſons of the Year muſt always be, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they cannot be: And this I take to be the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of our <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> (in this cauſe) now ſtated.</p>
               <p>Again, the like alſo, they ſay of any man's Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, That from the Influences of the Stars, all things are ordained, and appointed out for them, and what ſhall betide them here in this World; and therefore, whether it be good, or evil, they ſay, Men muſt be contented with their Fate. And ſo it appears by their (Opinion,) that every one by the Influences of the <hi>Stars,</hi> muſt be either Good or Evil, more or leſs, in their ſeveral Degrees, and Qualifications, of their Minds, as well as Rich or Poor in Fortunes; for I do not underſtand, that they do any of them (make any exception) in theſe things; and if ſo, then thoſe <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> make room for <hi>Atheiſm</hi> alſo. And indeed, great pity it is, that ſo many Wiſe Men, in Worldly Affairs, ſhould be ſo ignorant in that point, as to put any Confidence in ſuch Lying Fops, as many of them
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34674:44"/>are, whoſe very [<hi>Predictions</hi> give themſelves (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions) by which any Man may ſee, that they all of them err in their Art or Judgment, in ſuch high degrees, as that the beſt of their Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; deſerve to be deſpiſed, and contemned, for thereby they do pretend to know the very Secrets of God himſelf, which is impoſſible for any Man to know; and I queſtion, whether the Angels in Heaven do know what ſhall betide every Man on Earth, until God himſelf is pleaſed to reveal ſuch things to them, when he ſends them forth as his Meſſengers, to execute his Will either in Mercy, or Judgment, to good or evil Men, whilſt they are here upon the Earth: And therefore if ſuch Secrets are not known to Angels, how came they to be known to ſuch Men, (as call themſelves <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>) who are in themſelves, ſome of them, almoſt as bad as <hi>Devils;</hi> and I had no need to have ſaid, almoſt as bad, for the very <hi>Devils themſelves believe and tremble:</hi> But ſuch Men as do pretend to this great Art in <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> ſome of them, have as I have been told, deny'd the very Being of God himſelf. But however, I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways own and honour all ſuch Men, as have this great knowledge, of the Motions of the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies (provided) they do not go beyond their Laſt, or Station; for they are very uſeful to us (all) to know the Times and Seaſons of the Year. And I hope ſome of them do believe in the (one) and only true God, and alſo, do allow him to be the (only) whole and ſole Creator of Heaven and Earth; and that he can and doth many times alter and change the Courſes of thoſe Heavenly Bodies, for to ſerve his own purpoſe (how) and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34674:44"/>when he pleaſeth, (or) otherwiſe, it would be very ſad, if all of them ſhould be Atheiſtically minded: But I have more Charity for ſome of them, than ſo to think of them; but for any of their abſolute Predictions, I take them to be very vain, and fooliſh, and think it great Folly, in any one, to fear them, or any way, in the leaſt, to depend upon them; for certainly, no Man can tell, what ſhall betide a Child, by his knowing the very Minuit of the Hour that he was born into the World; for ſuch things as theſe, are Secrets, which are known to none but God himſelf; and I do aver it, that it is above and beyond the Art of any Man in the World, to foretell punctually, every thing that ſhall betide any Man here in this ſubluminary World: And ſuch things as theſe ſome <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> pretend to foretell; and ſome Men there be now living, that do put too muſt truſt in them, and ſeem to plead for the certainty of their knowledge; for ſay they, <hi>Some of them do ramble very right in ſome of their Predictions.</hi> To which I anſwer, The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Fool in Nature, may ſometimes by chance, anſwer aptly to ſome Queſtions; but 'tis very rare that they do ſo, and it is altogether ſo rare a thing, to ſee or know any of their Predictions, to fall out ſo patly to their purpoſes, as Fools do ſometimes by chance ſo patly anſwer the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions put to them. But as to the truth of any of their Predictions, they are very uncertain things, and much more uncertain, than any Lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries whatſoever; for in them, there are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome Prizes, for the many Blanks that do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them: But there is no certainty at all, for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34674:45"/>the very truth of any of the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> Predictions whatſoever, that they ſhall really come to paſs, as they predicted it. But however, for Argument-ſake, I think it fit to compair their Predictions, to be ſomewhat like unto Lotteries, as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties of them; for a Man may looſe, much Money to a Lottery, before he may get one Prize; and yet notwithſtanding that now and than by the turn of an accidental Die, after many throws, there may at laſt turn up a Prize. And ſo amongſt ſo many of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (now) and than, accidentally, ſome things may happen to fall out, to be ſomewhat like, what they had before predicted in ſuch dark Problems as they uſually utter them, which have alſo in them a very large relation, to many other common Accidents, that uſually do fall out many times: But then if any of theſe Accidents agree with their Predictions, (then) the whole World is not untold of it, by themſelves, (altho') at the ſame time, thoſe <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> by their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing Skill, knew nothing of the (reality) of ſuch things, that it ſhould certainly come to paſs: But their Predictions are ſo variouſly expreſt, that they will bear ſeveral. Conſtructions, And (by that way) Chance-medlee, may bring to paſs, now and than, ſome little things, ſomething like to what they predicted, which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> will be ſure to catch at, and will ſay, That, that was the thing they meant in their Predictions, when (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) 'twas never in their thoughts bfeore, (only) they will allow it to be ſo, when any ſuch thing ſo falls out to ſerve their turn.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34674:45"/>
               <p>But again, (if I miſtake not) the very Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all their Art, is grounded, on no better bottom, than from the obſervation of Antient <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> who did then, in their days, both quote, and chronicle, the ſeveral Poſitions, of the heavenly Bodies, and the Effects which enſued in their time, and ſo have left it down to our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, That it was their Judgments, that when the heavenly Bodies, ſhould be at any time, after their time, in the ſame Poſitions, that they were (then) in their time, that (then) the ſame like Effects would follow again, that did happen to be and fall out in their time, (whilſt they were then living) which (preſident) is to me no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reaſon, nor can it, as I think, be a ſufficient Reaſon to ſatisfie any rational Man; for li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Cauſes have not always their like Effects, as may be ſeen in many things throughout the whole Courſe of Nature, (and in ſuch things too) as is plainly within our ſelves known for certain Truths. For I my ſelf have ſometimes made Obſervation, of ſome red louring Evenings, juſt after Sun-ſet; and ſuch Signs as theſe, ſome ſay, are tokens of a very foul Rainy-day, the next day following: But yet it hath not happened to be ſo always; tho' this I have obſerv'd of it, that ſometimes ſuch a very wet Day hath followed ſuch an Evening. But then again, I have obſerved, that as often it hath fallen out to the contrary. Again, I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that ſometimes in an Evening, the Sky hath been very clear, and the Air very calm, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, the Sun hath ſet very gloriouſly, and ſome Weather-mongers do ſay, (that) is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſign of a Fair Day, next to fellow; and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34674:46"/>yet oftentimes it falleth out, that we have had the very next day, a very wet Rainy-day.—The like alſo may be ſaid concerning the <hi>Winds,</hi> for the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Eaſt</hi> Winds are uſually cold and dry; and the <hi>South</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> Winds uſually more warm and moiſt, and more inclinable to Wet Weather: And yet ſometimes, the <hi>South</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> Winds, are ſomewhat dry and cold, as the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Eaſt</hi> Winds are ſometimes more warm and moiſt; and in theſe things, as well as in many others that I could mention, all, like Cauſes have not their like Effects. But again, as to the Weather, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain a thing that is, every one knows, that has (Eyes) to ſee the variable changes of it, and yet our <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> will take it upon them, to foretell it to the whole Country: And indeed, I muſt ſay it, that it is a foul ſhame to all our <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers,</hi> to write ſo many genteel Complements, if not Lyes it ſelf (about the Weather) for ſome of them, do point-blank, ſay wet Weather, when at the ſame time, the Weather proveth to be very dry: And when they ſay very Cold, then it doth very commonly fall out to be very Warm for the time of the Year: And when they down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly ſay, Snow or Sleet; then moſt commonly, according to the ſeaſon of the Year, it is then very fair and warm; but when they ſay fair Halcyon days for a long time together, then methinks I am ſure of Rain, becauſe by woful Experience, I have found it ſo in my Journeys on Horſe-back, when I have been ſeveral times, ſoundly Wet in through all my Cloaths, in to my very Skin, and the Rain hath then dropt out of the Elbows of my Coat-Sleeves in the time of their <hi>Halcyon</hi>-days;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34674:46"/>and therefore, I'll depend no more on their <hi>Halcyon</hi>-days, for conſtant Fair Weather.—But again, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers</hi> will ſay, That there is not that certain Rule, for the Knowledge of the Weather, as their is for the Calculating of Nativities: For ſay they, the innumerable Company of Stars, (are fix't) and move not at all, but in their grand Motion, and the Seven Planets, keep their due Courſes, (always) according to their ſeveral Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But as for thoſe lower Airel Regions, they are often-times loaded with putrified Atoms, and much moiſt matter, with other combuſtable Stuff wich is always on where or other (huft) and (puft) to and fro, and with great violence (toſt,) up and down, here and there, in thoſe low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Regions of Air; for when the (Air) which is in it ſelf pure, doth find it ſelf thus bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, then it will by courſe of Nature, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to free it ſelf, and never reſt quiet, until it be done: And therefore, no wonder is to be made of it (at all) altho' we <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do ſo very much fail in theſe our Predictions about the Weather.</p>
               <p>To this I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> (and ſay) you (Maſters) and <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> what you do now offer in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, concerning your Miſtakes, in and about the Weather, I muſt confeſs, that it doth appear to me, to be very rationable, and I apt to believe, what you ſay in this matter, may be very true: But yet, however (Gentlemen) I muſt tell you, that you are much to be blamed, to put ſuch Tricks upon the poor ignorant Country-men, that do put ſo much Truſt and Confidence in you, and believe all that you ſay in your <hi>Almanacks</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Weather to be true. And I believe,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34674:47"/>many of them, do ſo order their Buſineſs, as to Plow and Sow their Seeds, at ſuch times as your <hi>Almanacks,</hi> tells them that they may expect Fair Weather: But then, when thoſe Country-men find themſelves (ſo diſappointed) with ſuch wet Weather, as that they are hindred both from Plowing and Sowing their Seeds; then it may be ſome of them may be apt enough, to ſay their Prayers backward, on the behalf of their <hi>Almanack</hi>-Makers; for indeed, they are many of them ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant enough, and very prophane alſo, for I have been credibly informed of a certain Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom I very well knew, that on a certain time (ſaid) when he had Corn out in the Field, in Harveſt-time, and when his Corn was dry, and fit to be houſed, and then ſuddain Rain came on it again; then be, who was the Owner of the Corn, with a moroſe voice and frowning ill-lookt Countenance, caſt up his Eyes to Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and very Fooliſhly, Bruitiſhly, and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or Atheiſtically then ſaid theſe Words, <hi>(Ay) (do) God Almighty, do, ſpoil all, do ſo; do.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſay, you <hi>Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> if ſuch men are ſo apt to blaſpheme or mock at God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when the Weather doth not pleaſe them, what is it that they will not ſay of you <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> when they find how often you have deceived them with your falſe Predictions about the Weather.</p>
               <p>But again, I muſt have the other touch, with you <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> about your Predictions. And now I ſay, I have heard, that there hath been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation made (of two Children) who were both born in one (hour) of the ſame Day, and as near, as it could be gueſt at, within a Minuit or two's
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34674:47"/>time; and alſo, they were (both) equal in Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and Fortune, as to their Birth, and yet, they [both] had not, equal Fortune in the World alike, for one of them, 'tis ſaid, lived but poor and meanly; but the other grew very Rich and Weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, (altho') the Man whoſe Fortune was to be poor, was altogether ſo well accompliſht, as to natural parts, and every way ſo temperate a man, and altogether ſo frugal, in his Worldly buſineſs, as he could be, that was born into the World, with him that grew ſo rich: (And therefore) pray Mr. <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> what was the Reaſon, why one of them was ſo Poor, and the other ſo Rich?</p>
               <p>Mr. Aſtrologer. <hi>I'll anſwer you Sir, to this; the Reaſon was, becauſe they were not Born both together in the ſame Minuit, or Moment of time; for one Moment may make ſome alteration, in ſuch Cauſes; for if they had been both Born into the World (in one) and the ſame Minuit, or rather Moment of Time, then I do aver it, that they would both of them, have had very nearly (if not) equal ſucceſs in thoſe their Worldly Affairs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Sir, was this the very Reaſon, why theſe Men were ſo different, in their worldly Fortune?</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>Yes, Sir, that was the very reaſon of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> I do not believe it: But however, provided, it be true, that every Man's good or evil Fate, doth depend upon that very critical point of Time, pray Sir, where is that Man or Woman in the World, that is either Father or Mother, of any Child, whoſe Nativity you have ever calculated, that could ever tell the very Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Minuit, or Moment of Time, of their Childs Birth?</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34674:48"/>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>Yes Sir, very well, there be them that have obſerved the very Minuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> By what rule, Sir?</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer <hi>By Clocks, Watches, and Sun-Dials, or by the Courſes of the Sun, Moon, and Stars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> But what if the Sun, Moon, or Stars, are not to be ſeen, either [by Day] or by Night, by reaſon of dark, thick, groſs Clouds, that may interpoſe between us and them, ſo as that neither of them could, or can, or may be ſeen at the time of the Birth of any Child? or how can you, or how will you, or how could you, ever know the very exact Minuit or Moment of Time in ſuch Weather?</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>Why, then we muſt trust to Clocks, or Watches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Ay, ſurely, that way you muſt needs be deceived, in the knowing the very exact minuit, or moment of the time, of any Child's Birth: For where is that Watch, or Clock to be found in the whole World, that doth always keep the true time of the Day and Night (ſo exactly) as not to fail, in one minuit or moment's time? Or if there could be any ſuch Clock, or Watch (made) that would keep time ſo (exactly,) where is that Man in the world, that can ſet any Clock or Watch, ſo exact to the very time, of the Day, or Night, as that he doth not err in one minuit, or moment's time, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the very real time (of the Day or Night) and exactly agreeable, to the time, as by the Courſes, and Motions of the Sun, Moon, and Stars, it is meaſured out (and divided?)</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>There are Men, that can make a Watch, or Clock, that will conſtantly carry the true
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34674:48"/>time, of the Day or Night, when it is once but truly ſet by the Sun Dial, I ſay to a moment of time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Sir, I do not believe that; tho' for Argument-ſake, if I allow it ſo, yet I have this to ſay; Pray, Sir, where is the Man to be found, in the whole World, that can meaſure the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Orbs ſo (exactly,) as from that Rule, to be able to ſet, any Sun-Dial, ſo (exactly) true, as that it ſhall ſhew the very (exact) time of the Day, exactly, agreeing with the (exact) time meaſured out, by the [due] and daily, and nightly, Courſes of the Sun, Moon, and Stars.</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>Sir, there be them, that can do theſe things, which you queſtion the truth of it, whether you will believe it, or not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Sir, I muſt ſay ſtill, I do not believe, that any man in the world, can make any ſuch Clock, Watch, or Sun-Dial, that will keep true Time (exactly) and equally, not erring one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, from the true time, of the day or night, as it is exactly meaſured out or divided out by the Courſes, or Motions of the Sun, Moon and Stars. And therefore, upon the whole of this our Argument, I muſt ſay, (provided) that I could allow that there is ſuch a thing, as Fate, or Deſtiny, and that it is decreed, by the Courſes of the Stars, every one's Fortune, what it ſhall be here in this Sublunary World; yet Sir, this muſt needs be a thing, beyond your knowledge, and impoſſible for you ever to know, the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it; for you your ſelf do allow in Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that for the doing of it truly, without er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in your Predictions, that you muſt know, the very moment, of the time, of any one's
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34674:49"/>Birth (whoſe Nativity) you will pretend to cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate (exactly;) and that exact and unerring time, is not to be found out: And therefore, I ſay, that Art muſt needs fail in its perfection, which hath an Error in its Foundation; and ſuch an Error, there is, in the foundation of your Art of Aſtrology. And now upon the whole of your Arguments, (I find) that you Aſtrologers, are as certain of your Art, in reference to your Predictions, if you could but find the very moment of the time, of any ones Birth, as that great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt was, in the ſtrength of his Engin, who ſaid, That he could by an (Engin) remove the whole (maſs) of Earth out of his place, provided, he could but find a firm Foundation, to reſt on, or (fix) his Engin upon it.</p>
               <p>And now to conclude our Diſcourſes, I ſay, no ſuch Foundation could ever be found, for ſuch an Engin to reſt upon; nor can I believe, that the very exact moment of time, can ever be found out, for you to work by it without Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; and therefore, it is certainly ſo, that you muſt needs err, and fail in all your Calculations and Predictions whatſoever, and there is no more truth, in any thing you ſay, concerning Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than their is in that which you ſay about the Weather; and every man, that hath ever made Obſervation on time paſt, (doth know) how ſhamefully, you all of you, and the beſt of you Aſtrologers, have of late Years, failed in your Predictions; and you your ſelves do well know, that the whole Art of Aſtrology, is meerly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, only you muſt for Self-intereſt-ſake, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, to maintain, and uphold it, becauſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34674:49"/>(perhaps) your very livelihood much depends (upon) the uſing of this fallible Art; and all your Predictions in time (are found) to be meer idle, fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, fooliſh, and vain Sayings; nor can I think any man wiſe, that doth, or will, put any truſt and confidence, in the certainty of your Predictions, or in any other Sayings (of you Aſtrologers) in or about any ſuch matters, as is before-mentioned,</p>
               <p>But as for <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> that I will allow, to be a noble, lawful, and honourable Science; for they plainly demonſtrate, what they pretend to know, and for the moſt part of it, the truth of it, is, effectually found; but as to any thing concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art of Aſtrology, I think it, not worth the while, to diſcourſe you, any more about it; and ſo fair you well, Sir.</p>
               <p>Aſtrologer. <hi>Pray, Sir, before we part, let me ask you a Queſtion; What ſay you, is the reaſon, why thoſe two Men were ſo unequal in their Worldly Fortunes? (ſeeing) they were both equal in their (Births) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, Parts, Education, and in all manner of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications; and alſo, were both born into the World, in one and the ſame Hour, and Minuit as it were, they both of them, came into the World together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Sir, I will Anſwer your Queſtion: The reaſon of it (was this) God) that made them, and ſent them both into the World (at) or nearly at one and the very ſame time, he for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf, thought it not fit, to give them an equal ſhare alike of worldly Goods, or ſuch things as we call Riches, (altho') he was then pleaſed, to make them both equal in Qualifications, as to their natural tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Body and Mind, [and that] becauſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34674:50"/>it was his pleaſure ſo to do, [or] it may be [God] that foreknoweth all things, did then foreſee, that a mean condition, was beſt for him, to whoſe Lot it fell to; for Riches are not always the beſt Gifts to ſome men, and (yet) there is no harm in them, if they are not abuſed in the ill uſing of them: But this I know, ſome men that have them, may do much more good with them, than they do, if they would but do as they are required; but their own covetous Hearts will not permit them ſo to do: And for ought I know, therefore it is, that God doth often-times, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſome Rich Men, to be enſnared, by the means of their own Riches. And what a ſtrickt charge [Chriſt] himſelf gives to all men, to avoid Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and the Evils of it; you may read it in the 12th Chapter of St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Goſpel, verſ. 15. theſe words, <hi>And he ſaid unto them, Take heed and beware of Covetouſneſs, for a Man's Life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi> Again, I ſay, is it not oftentimes ſeen, how Riches puffs up ſome Men into Pride, and makes them oftentimes undertake, the doing of many unjuſt things, which many times, brings them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Snares of a temporal (and ſhameful Death) and therefore, I ſay again, that (God) foreſees, that Riches are not the beſt Temporal Gifts for ſome men, and for ought I know, Riches are with-holden from ſome men, in a way of Mercy, as they may for ought I know (be given) to ſome other Men, in a way of Judgment: But to whomſoever they are given, (yet) they are given to them, (only) for to do good with them, in this their Generation; which if they do not ſo do, (then)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34674:50"/>it will be required at their Hands, for theſe things, are their ſeveral Talents, and God giveth theſe Talents of Riches to whom he pleaſeth, to ſome more, and to ſome leſs: But (yet) never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, he always requireth from every one, even as he hath given to him, for even ſo as his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is, even ſo thereafter he ought to improve it; for where much is given, much is required: read the 25th Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, beginning at the 15th Verſe, and ſo onwards to the 31 Verſe.</p>
               <p>And now, I ſay again, It is the Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Almighty, to deal with us his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as he pleaſeth, and to give [us] of theſe worldly things, more or leſs, as he thinks (is) or may be beſt for us: And that was the reaſon (why) one of thoſe two Men, which were born into the World, even as it were at one and the ſame time, was but poor and mean, in reference to temporal Riches, whilſt the other (might,) for ought I know, ſuperabonnd in his abundance. But who ſhall dare ask God, Why doſt thou ſo? For may not God, do with his own what he pleaſeth, and give to every one (more) or leſs, as he pleaſeth. Yes, he may, and he doth beſtow it (where) and (how) he pleaſeth, and from his Hands alone; by his divine way of Providence, cometh all our Riches, or Poverty, [excepting] what the meer Sluggard bringeth upon himſelf; for he ſhall be cloathed with Rags, (as the Wiſe Man ſaith) for God doth require a means to be uſed by all men: But however, without God's Bleſſings, to the Means, which we uſe, all our Labour will be in vain; for 'tis not he that riſeth in the Morning
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34674:51"/>early, nor he that goeth to Bed late, (or) eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Bread of Carefulneſs; (Nor) can any Man, by his care, wiſdom, or ſtrength alone, procure to himſelf theſe worldly things; for ſee what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith concerning this matter, in the 9th Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> verſ. 11.—<hi>I returned, and ſaw under the Sun, that the Race is not to the ſwift, nor the Lattel to the strong, neither yet Bread to the Wiſe, nor yet Riches to men of understanding, nor yet favour to men of skill, but Time and Chance happeneth to them all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But again, you Aſtrologers, (perhaps) may queſtion and ſay, <hi>Pray Sir, what doth the Wiſe Man (mean) by his ſaying, But Time and Chance hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth to them all? For by theſe his own Words, it ſeems to us, as if they were ſpoken in favour of our Science.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author.</hi> Sirs, this Queſtion I will endeavour to anſwer you alſo; and now I ſay, <hi>Solomon,</hi> by them Words, doth not mean any ſuch Chances, as you Aſtrologers do ſay, doth betide every man, according to his Fate, or Deſtiny, as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed above, and that [only] from the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Power, which you ſay, the Stars have over every Man here on Earth, (accordingly) as the ſeveral Poſitions of them, were in the very Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, or Moment of timet he of every man's Birth. For <hi>Solomon,</hi> in another place of this his ſame Book: declares expreſly againſt you, and in effect by his Words there expreſt (to me) it doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, as if he had there poſitively meaned, at that very time, when he writ them Words, that, that art of Aſtrology, as you now profeſs it, and practiſe it, then was, and now is altogether unattainable, and impoſſible to be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34674:51"/>known, by any Man that ever was, or ever ſhall be upon the Earth; look in <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> Chap. 8. Verſ. 17. And there you will find, <hi>Solomon</hi>'s words to be theſe as followeth; <hi>Then I beheld all the work of God, that a man cannot find out, the work that is done under the Sun: Becauſe though a man labour to ſeek it out, yet he ſhall not find it; yea further, though a Wiſe Man think to know it, yet ſhall he not be able to find it out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now upon the whole of our Arguments, between us, I farther ſay, Away with all your Predictions, for I cannot otherwiſe but abominate them; for theſe things which you pretend to know, are the very Secrets of [God] himſelf, and paſt your finding them out. And therefore it is not worth my labour, to diſcourſe you any more about it, [for Seeing] is Believing; and every Year, we find all your Predictions, ſo far from truth, that I think any of them not worth any man's Obſervation, (otherwiſe) than to laugh at them, and not to depend on them; nor can any man truly believe in God, that doth believe and put truſt in any of your Predictions; for how can any man believe in [God] that will not believe in the Holy Bible, which is God's Word, and ſpeaks directly againſt ſuch ones as you are, as you may read it in the 47th Chapter of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> verſ. 12, 13, 14. It is there thus writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Stand now with thine Inchantments, and with the multitude of thy Sorceries, wherein thou hast la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured from thy Youth, if ſo be thou ſhalt be able to profit, if ſo be thou mayest prevail. Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy Councils: Let now the Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, the Star-gazers, the Monthly Prognosticators,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34674:52"/>stand up and ſave thee. Behold, they ſhall be as stubble, the Fire ſhall burn them up, they ſhall not deliver themſelves from the power of the Flame.</hi> And thus by the written Word of God, you may ſee what a vain thing Aſtrology is; for all the Prophets of the Lord exclaimed againſt it.</p>
               <p>And now I ſay upon the whole of this my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, concerning Aſtrology, or Aſtrologers, both from Reaſon, and Scripture, it doth plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to me, that the whole Art of Aſtrology is fallible; and therefore it muſt needs be a vain and fooliſh thing, in any Perſon whatſoever, to put any truſt or confidence in any of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, or in the Predictions of any other Men, that are profeſſors of any other ſuch-like vain Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. And ſo for the preſent, I take my leave of you Aſtrologers, until it comes in my way to mention your Names again.</p>
               <p>And now by the courſe of Argument, I think it comes again in my way, to ſpeak ſomething more concerning our late Unfruitful Years, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall ſay farther as followeth.</p>
               <p>Both from Reaſon, and Scripture, it doth appear to me, that our late Long Winters, cold Springs, cold Summers, Wet Harveſts, and Unſeaſonable Sowing times, which hath been of late Years, [was not] wholly from the Natural Cauſes of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bodies, as they were from the Creation, firſt ordained in their Courſes: But, that it was from the immediate hand of God; (not) but that I will allow, that the Coeleſtial Bodies, do bear rule and govern over all our Terreſtrial Bodies; and that their ſeveral Influences, many ways, do
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34674:52"/>either afflict, or comfort us, while we are here on the Earth, as may be Daily, Weekly, Monthly, and Yearly ſeen, in and by the Revolution of that moſt glorious Planet the <hi>Sun,</hi> which for ought I know, may be the Centre, and there placed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it might be the better able, and more fit to diſtribute and ſend abroad his comfortable Beams; for we find by his warm Influences, that all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures here on Earth, both Rational, Senſative, and Vegitable, are comforted and cheriſhed, as ſoon as it approacheth towards us: And ſo on the contrary, we ſee, and find, that for want of the warm Influences of the <hi>Sun,</hi> all compounded Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Bodies whatſoever, that have in them Life, and are ſubject to alteration, do pine and droop, when it withdraws his comfortable Beams from us.</p>
               <p>Again, I do not ſay, but that all the reſt of the other Heavenly Bodies, have their ſhares, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of their ſeveral Influences, on all ſuch Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies, as aforeſaid, (one way) or other; for I believe [God] might make them for that uſe, as well as for Signs, and for Seaſons, and for Days, and Years: But the moſt ſecret uſe of them, is [only] known to God himſelf, and it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any Man, to reach to the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch things, as <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> pretend to know. And therefore, I ſay again, it is idle and fooliſh, for any one to put truſt in Aſtrologers Predictions; for it was only [God] that at firſt created all thoſe Heavenly Bodies, and it is (only) he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that governs over them, and ruleth them in their ſeveral motions, how and which way he pleaſeth, and he altereth all their ſeveral Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34674:53"/>when he pleaſeth, and how he pleaſeth, (and that) to and for what Uſes, or Purpoſes, he pleaſeth; as we may ſee it made manifeſt in his moſt Holy Word in ſeveral places, and by ſeveral Preſidents; and the firſt that I ſhall quote you to this purpoſe, ſhall be that of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> in whoſe Book I find, that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> did by a ſubtil way obtain their Peace with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who by his League then promiſed that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſhould live; and alſo therein I find, that the Princes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſwore unto the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> alſo, that they ſhould not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: And more I find, that after the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> underſtood, by what an undermining way, they had obtained their Peace; then they were in great wroth with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and the Children of the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then murmured againſt their Princes, becauſe they had Peace with the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> and yet nevertheleſs, notwithſtanding that Peace, I find that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have deſtroyed the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites,</hi> had not the Princes of their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion told them, that they might not touch the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> becauſe they the Princes had ſworn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> that they ſhould live; as you may read it at large in the 9th Chapter of the Book of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> And from thence I obſerve this alſo, that their is a moſt ſacred tye (in Oaths) and that God doth expect from all men, that all manner of legal Oaths, made and ſworn, to good Intentions, as they have relation (only) to the Glory of God, and the Good of all Mankind, ſhould be always performed, and kept unviolated, as we may ſee by this League and Oath, between
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34674:53"/>the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> And tho' the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> did at that time, by ſuch a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling kind of way, obtain their League of Peace with the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet it was ſomewhat excuſable in them, becauſe they did it (only) to ſave their Lives, and not to ſave their Money, for they the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> offered up both themſelves and all that they had, ſaying to <hi>Joſhua, And now behold, we are in thine Hand, as it ſeemeth good and right unto thee (to do unto us) do;</hi> as you may read it in the ſame 9th Chapter of the Book of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> verſ. 24, 25, 26, 27. Again I ſay, that action of the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> is to be thought ſomewhat the more excuſeable, if we do but conſider with our ſelves how good and faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> did the like, when for fear of Death, he ſaid to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> that his Wife <hi>Sarah</hi> was his Siſter, and alſo <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf perſwaded <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife to ſay the like alſo, to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> look in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Chap. 12. verſ. 13. and ſo onwards to the end thereof. But again (I ſay) good Mens Evaſions are no ſufficient Warrants to allow evil Men in their moſt Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Wicked Actions; (And) there is a vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Mens evading of Truth (only) to ſave their own Lives, and that, of being Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Perjuries</hi> both towards God and Men (only) for to get (or) ſave a little Money; for that Sin, of evading Truth, (only) to ſave (Life it ſelf) may be forgiven, in and through the Mercy of God, barely, by a true Repentance for it: But Frauds, and Perjuties, are not forgiven (by Repentance alone) for Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo, muſt be made to ſuch People, as by their Frauds and Perjuries, they have any
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34674:54"/>way wrouged. But I muſt leave this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary digreſſion, and now proceed onwards to ſet forth my now deſigned matter: And ſo I ſay, I alſo find, that when the five Kings of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> went up to Encamp before the City of <hi>Gibeon;</hi> (then) the men of <hi>Gibeon</hi> ſent unto <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the Camp of <hi>Gilgal,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Slack not thy hand from thy ſervants; come up to us quickly, and ſave us, and help us, for all the Kings of the</hi> Amorites, <hi>that dwell in the mountains, are gathered together againſt us.</hi> And then I find (immediately) upon the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> requeſt, <hi>Joſhua</hi> with all the mighty men of valour, aſcended from <hi>Gilgal;</hi> and then the Lord, to encourage <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſaid unto them, <hi>Fear them not, for I have delivered them into thine hand, there ſhall not a man of them ſtand before thee.</hi> And thus <hi>Joſhua</hi> was encouraged by the Lord, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went up from <hi>Gilgal</hi> all Night, and came ſuddenly upon them; and then, as the Scripture-Text ſaith, <hi>The Lord diſcomfited them before</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and ſlew them with a great ſlaughter at</hi> Gibeon, <hi>and chaſed them along the way, that goeth to</hi> Beth-horon, <hi>and ſmote them to</hi> Azekah, <hi>and unto</hi> Mak-kedah. And more, the Text ſaith this, <hi>And it came to paſs, as they fled from before</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and were in the going down to</hi> Beth-horon, <hi>that the Lord cast down great Hail-ſtones from Heaven upon them, unto</hi> Aze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah, <hi>and they died.</hi> And then the Text ſaith, in theſe words, <hi>[They were more] which died with the Hail-ſtones, than they whom the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſlew with the Sword.</hi> And more the Text ſaith, <hi>Then ſpake</hi> Joſhua <hi>to the Lord, in the day when the Lord delivered up the</hi> Amorites <hi>before the Children of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>and be ſaid in the ſight of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Sun, ſtand thou ſtill
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34674:54"/>upon</hi> Gibeon, <hi>and thou Moon in the valley of</hi> Ajalon. <hi>And the Sun ſtood ſtill, and the Moon ſtayed [untill] the People had avenged themſelves upon their Enemies.</hi> And then the Text ſaith, <hi>Is not this written in the Book of</hi> Jaſher? <hi>So the Sun ſtood ſtill in the midſt of Heaven, and haſted not to go down, about a whole Day. And there was no Day, like that before it, or after it, that the Lord hearkened to the Voice of a Man.</hi> All this at large you may read it, in the 10th Chapter of the Book of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> And now the uſe that I ſhall make of this, is as followeth.</p>
               <p>And <hi>first</hi> of all, I find, that notwithſtanding the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> ſeveral evaſions, which they uſed in making up their League of Peace, with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet God was pleaſed to own them, (becauſe) he knew, that the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> in their Hearts believed in his Word, and dreaded his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and what they then did, [God] himſelf (knew) that it was not to deceive the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of any of their worldly Riches, or to do them any bodily harm; (but) that it was (only) out of an innocent fear, to ſave their own Lives; for they then thought with themſelves, that if they ſhould then have appeared plainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that then they ſhould not have obtained their Peace with <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And by this we may ſee, that in all things, God obſerves the Wills of Men, and that he takes for their Deeds, whether it be in things that are good, or whether it be in things that are evil.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> I find, that at any time whatſoever, when God ſhall think it fit, he can then (immediately) augment, or diminiſh, the Forces, (or) Influences, of all the Heavenly Bodies, (or) change, or ſtop
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34674:55"/>the courſes of the Sun, Moon, or Stars, (or) he can continue, (or) alter the whole Frame of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and from (order) turn into diſorder, all the other Elementary parts of this World what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, and how often ſoever, and that to what uſe or purpoſe ſoever, whether in ways of Mercy, or Judgment. And therefore, I ſay again, that it muſt by theſe Arguments conſequently follow, that all theſe our late Unfruitful Years, were by the (immediate) and Providential Hand of God ſo ordered to be; and Not by the Natural Courſes of the Heavenly Bodies (only) and accordingly to their firſt Ordination, as our <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it ſo to be: But how diſagreeable, ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are to the Word of God, I ſay judge ye. But the Word of God is true, (and) thereby I have made it manifeſt, that the Art of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> is a fallible Art; and for the better Confirmation of it, I cannot well omit that Preſident of good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> for when the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> told him, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Set thy Houſe in order, for thou ſhalt dye, and not live.</hi> Then immediately <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> turned his Face to the Wall, and with Prayers, and Tears, pleaded with God, [how] he had walked before him, in Truth, and with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Heart: Which prevailed ſo far with the Lord, that he altered his Decrec, and before <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was gone out of the middle Court of the Houſe or Palace of King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> the Lord commanded the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to return back to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and to tell him, That the Lord had heard his Prayer, and ſeen his Tears, for which he would heal him of his Sickneſs, and alſo on the third day, he ſhould be able to go up into the Houſe of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34674:55"/>the Lord; as alſo, that the Lord would then add unto the Days of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> Fifteen Years: But <hi>Hezekiah</hi> having on his Spirit ſome doubt, deſired a Sign, whereby he might know, that the Lord would heal him; which deſire of good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> God complyed with, and gave him a Sign, which was, that the Sun ſhould go backwards ten De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; which thing was made manifeſt, by the Shadows going backwards ten Degrees, after it was gone down ten Degrees in the Dial of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> as you may read it at large, in the ſecond Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> the 20th Chapter, from the beginning of that Chapter, unto the 12th Verſe. And this I offer at large (only) to prove, that God can as well (now) in our days, take off the warm Beams, and moſt comfortable Influences of the Sun from the Earth, by way of Judgment, on the Wicked, as well as to make the Sun go backwards from his Courſe, by way of Mercy, for a Sign (only) to ſatisfie the doubt of one ſingle Man, and that (becauſe) he had in him an upright and perfect Heart.</p>
               <p>And now, I ſay, by this place of Scripture, as well as in ſeveral other places of Scripture, we may ſee, that Prayers, and Tears, prevailed much with God, when they have been offered up unto him, with a true, devout, and ſincere Heart; for were not <hi>David</hi>'s Prayers heard by the Lord, and his deſires, granted unto him, from time, to time, when he Prayed, that he might be delivered out of his Afflictions, and from the Malice of his Enemies; read all his <hi>Pſalms</hi> throughout, and in many of them, you will find, how much, <hi>David</hi> depended upon Prayers, and how often from
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34674:56"/>time to time, <hi>David</hi>'s requeſt was granted to him by Prayer. Again, I ſay, read the firſt Chapter of the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> but more particularly obſerve the 10th verſe, and ſo onwards to the 21ſt verſe, and there you may find, how much the Prayers of <hi>Hannah,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Elkanah,</hi> prevailed with the Lord, when they were by her offered up with Tears, in the bitterneſs of her Soul; and altho' <hi>Ely</hi> the Prieſt, thought ſhe had been drunken, yet at the ſame time, ſhe was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly muttering within her ſelf in Prayer, and tho' her Lips only moved, yet in her Heart ſhe ſpake unto the Lord, and deſired of him a Man-child, which God in proceſs of time granted unto her, and not only a meer Man-child, did the Lord give unto <hi>Hannah,</hi> but ſuch a Man-child, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards became an excellent Prophet of the Lord, whoſe Name was <hi>Samuel:</hi> And after that, I find (beſides <hi>Samuel,</hi>) <hi>Hannah</hi> had by her Husband <hi>Elkanah,</hi> ſeveral Sons and Daughters, as you may read it in the 2d. Chapter of the 1ſt. Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> verſ. 21. And thus we may ſee by thoſe Preſidents offered, and mentioned in theſe ſeveral Scriptures herein quoted, and alſo, by ſeveral other places of Scripture, the like Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents may be found, and by all of them it may be plainly ſeen, how much Prayers, and Tears, have always, from time, to time, prevailed with God, when they have been offered up unto him, with true, devout, and ſincere Hearts; and therefore, I think, it would not be amiſs, but rather think it very neceſſary, and needful for us all, with true devotion, now to offer up our Prayers with Tears, and deſire God to give every one of us, a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34674:56"/>Heart fit for true Repentance, and Amendment of Life; which if we would all of us ſo pray, and endeavour ſo to do, then no queſtion might be made of it, but that God would yet ſhew us mercy, and then we ſhould have the Bleſſings of the Lord return upon us, which now ſeems to be departing from us; Read the ſecond Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> verſ. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Therefore alſo now ſaith the Lord, Turn ye even unto me with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mourning. And rent your heart, and not your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and turn unto the Lord your God; for he is gracious and merciful, ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſs, and repenteth him of the evil. Who knoweth if he will return and repent, and leave a Bleſſing behind him, even a Meat-offering, and a Drink-offering unto the Lord your God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But again, I ſay, that God doth ſometimes by the diſorder of the Elementary Parts of this World, bring upon the Earth, <hi>Dearths</hi> and <hi>Famine</hi> it ſelf, (is plain) by what God himſelf made known to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his Dream, for God did not only make known unto him, that he would bring a Famine upon the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but by what means the Famine ſhould come, was alſo made known unto <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in his Dream, (and that to be) by means of unſeaſonable Weather, as violent Eaſt-Winds, which ſhould blaſt and wither the Corn-Fields, ſo as that they ſhould come to no perfection, to bear Corn for the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to have Bread out of them; as you may read it in the 41 Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the 6th, the 23d, and 27th verſes.</p>
               <p>Again, I ſay, that God [hath,] and yet [can] by his immediate Power, that he hath over all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34674:57"/>the Elementary Bodies, alter and change the Weather, as he ſeeth moſt fit, either by way of Mercy, or Judgment, is plain: And alſo, that it is mens Iniquities, that doth oftentimes provoke God, to bring upon the Earth, Dearths, and Wants, and Famine it ſelf, is plainly to be ſeen, and underſtood, if men would but conſult ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly within themſelves, theſe following Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which I ſhall here quote unto you, which you may read at your leiſure, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 5th Chap. verſ. 24, 25. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 4th Chap. verſ. 16, 17. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2d Chap. verſ. 8, 9. Read <hi>Joel</hi> the 1ſt Chapter, all over from the beginning, to the end thereof. <hi>Amos</hi> 4th Chapter, verſ. 6, 7. And laſtly, look in the 14th Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> verſ. 12, 13, 14. It is there thus written, <hi>The Word of the Lord came again to me, ſaying, Son of Man, when the Land ſinneth against me by treſpaſſing grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly, then will I stretch out mine hand upon it, and will break the Staff of the Bread thereof, and will ſend Famine upon it, and will cut off Man and Beast from it: Though theſe three Men,</hi> Noah, Daniel, <hi>and</hi> Job, <hi>were in it, they ſhould deliver but their own Souls by their Righteouſneſs, ſaith the Lord God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus we may ſee, that when Men, by their Iniquities, do provoke God to anger, then, in his Wrath he immediately, changeth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordereth the Heavenly Bodies, or other Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Parts of the World, as he pleaſeth: And thus working by his own ſecondary Cauſes, as he thinks moſt fit, he can when he pleaſeth, with hold theſe good things of the World from us; and alſo, from this laſt Text of Scripture, juſt now here quoted, we may obſerve, that when
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34674:57"/>the black Deeds of the Wicked, are many, and that they are ſo much over-grown, that they do ſuperabound; then, the Prayers of the Righteous can prevail with God (no longer) to prevent the pouring down of his Judgments upon the Heads of Wicked Men: For then, the Prayers of the Righteous, (only) for the deliverance of their own Souls, ſhall be heard, and not for the Souls of the Wicked. And now I ſay again, theſe before-mentioned Scriptures do make it out plain, That all Diſorders, both in Heaven, and Earth, from time, to time, are always performed, by the immediate Hand of God, and [not] as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers ſay (only) from the Courſes of the Stars, as they were ordained to be in their firſt Creation.</p>
               <p>And therefore I muſt now ſay again, that no Aſtrologers, (or) any other Men, of any other (vain) Sciences whatſoever, (can foretell) by the Courſes of the Stars, (or) by any other way whatſoever, what ſhall fall out, or come to paſs, either of Plague or Famine, (or) what ſhall be the event of Wars, (or) who ſhall have the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, (or) foreknow, by the Calculating of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivities, what ſhall befall any Man, or Men, (or) what Years will be fruitful (or) unfruitful; for all theſe things are Secrets, and only belong to God himſelf, and not unto Men, except out of his own goodneſs, and meer pleaſure (in Mercy) to ſome of his own choſen Ones, he is pleaſed to reveal theſe his Secrets, to ſuch Men, as he thinks moſt fit, to pour out his Spirit upon them, to that purpoſe, and for that end, to preſerve his own People, as may be ſeen in that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34674:58"/>of <hi>Pharoah;</hi> for God did not forewarn <hi>Pharoah,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of what he was about to do, (wholly) for the ſake of <hi>Pharoah</hi> himſelf, or for the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſake; but (moſtly) for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and then conſequently, for the Preſervation of all the Children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> And therefore it was, that none of the Magicians, or any of the Wiſe Men of <hi>Egypt,</hi> could interpret <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Dream, for it was only God's choſen One, that could do it, who was <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and that not of himſelf, but by the Inſpiration of the Lord, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> himſelf (acknowledgeth) in this ſame 41 Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and the 16 verſe, It is there ſaid; <hi>And</hi> Joſeph <hi>anſwered</hi> Pharoah, <hi>ſaying, It is not in me, God ſhall give</hi> Pharoah <hi>an anſwer of Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again I ſay, that the Revelation of Secrets, doth only belong unto God, and not unto ſuch Men as are called <hi>Aſtrologers:</hi> But when God thinks fit, [he] revealeth them to his own choſen Ones, as you may read in the third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> verſ. 7. theſe words, <hi>Surely the Lord God will do nothing, but he revealeth his ſecret unto his Servants, the Prophets.</hi> And thus you may ſee by this Scripture alſo, it is plain that all Secret Things belong only to God himſelf, until ſuch times as he is pleaſed to make them known to ſome of his own choſen Ones, and that [only] upon ſome Extraordinary Occaſions, in order, to and for, the preſervation of God's Holy Ones, as may be ſeen alſo, in that of God's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the holy Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> on ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and that, by ſeveral ways and means, how he was from time to time, preſerved by God, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34674:58"/>alſo made an Inſtrument to preſerve other good Men, as you may read it in the ſecond Chapter of the Book of <hi>Daniel,</hi> verſ. 13. thus written, <hi>And the decree went forth, that the wiſe-men ſhould be ſlain, and they ſought</hi> Daniel, <hi>and his fellows, to be ſlain:</hi> And that only becauſe the <hi>Magicians,</hi> and the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> and the <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> and the <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans,</hi> could not Interpret, unto King <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> his Dream; (therefore) <hi>Daniel</hi> and his Fellows alſo, muſt be ſlain with them: But then, (God) for the manifeſtation of his own Power, as alſo, for the preſervation of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, (God) was then pleaſed to reveal that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret unto <hi>Daniel,</hi> which God himſelf had then before revealed unto King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and yet, at that time, God was pleaſed to deny unto King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the remembrance of his Dream, and that (only) becauſe God himſelf would make it more manifeſt, that it is himſelf only, that doth, (or can) reveal Secrets, and that only and immediately from himſelf, (or) by the Mouths of his own Choſen Ones; and this <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> himſelf acknowledgeth, as you may read it in Verſe 30. of this ſaid Chapter, it is there thus ſaid, <hi>But as for me, this Secret is not revealed to me, for any Wiſdom that I have more then any living: But for their ſakes that ſhall make known the Interpretation to the King, and that thou mighteſt know the thoughts of thy heart.</hi> And thus you may ſee, how <hi>Daniel</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth own the Power of revealing Secrets, to be in God above, (and himſelf) to be but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of it, as it was revealed unto him, from God, for which <hi>Daniel</hi> praiſed God; and alſo, he acknowledgeth, that all Power, all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and all Seaſons, and all People, even Princes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34674:59"/>as well as Subjects, are in the diſpoſing Hand of God, as you may read it, in this ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Book of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the 19th, 20th, 21, 22, and 23 verſes. And thus <hi>Daniel,</hi> and all the reſt of the Prophets of the Lord, they do all agree, that it is from the (immediate) power, of God alone, that all Seaſons are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, whether to Order (or) diſorder, fruitful (or) unfruitful, wet (or) dry, for it is only God that cauſeth it to Rain upon one Field, and not upon the other; and it is only him, that giveth a plentiful Crop of Corn to one Man, and a ſcanty Crop to another Man; and therefore (conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently) it muſt follow, that it is God alone, by his immediate Power, that hath of late changed, the ſmiling Influences of the Heavenly Bodies, and of late Years, hath made them look frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly upon us; (and) him alone it is, that of late, hath even as it were changed the whole: frame of Nature, (by means of which,) we have of late had, Year, after Year, but indifferent crops of Corn, which we Men (attribute) it, to no other Cauſe, than from the diſorderly Weather, which we have had of late Years: (And there are but few Men) that look to the Hand, from whence it came; or that it was only for our Sins, that God hath of late ſo diſordered the Weather: But be it for what it will, it is God that hath done it, and Time will make manifeſt, whether it be in a way (of Mercy) or Judgment.</p>
               <p>And now I think, it remaineth needful, that I ſhould give ſome Reaſons (wherefore) I have written ſo much againſt <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> and other Men of vain Sciences. And (therefore) my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34674:59"/>for it are theſe: By Experience, I find, that now in our Age, there be a great many People, and ſome, that do think themſelves Wiſe Men, that do now give more heed, unto what <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> do ſay, than they do to what God himſelf ſaith unto them in his Word; for it is now become a common thing, amongſt them, to go to <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers,</hi> to have Queſtions and Doubts, Anſwered and Reſolved; as alſo, to know what Succeſs they ſhall have in their Undertakings: And alſo to know, what Days are good, or evil, for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, of any material buſineſs; and if ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be not a forſaking of God, or at leaſt, a fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off from God, let any rational, or divine perſon judge. And great pity it is, that ſuch Men, ſhould have that liberty to act as they do, becauſe, what they do pretend to perform, doth take with many Vitious and Simple Ones; and when once ſome Atheiſtical Wretches, that have in them but a few Thundering Eloquent Words, and that they do but affirm the truth of <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> skill, in ſuch matters, then that doth much encourage others, that are but of weak Capacities, to believe in them likewiſe: And ſo by this way, more room is made for <hi>Atheiſm</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>And thus, by ſeveral ways, and methods, I have endeavoured to ſet forth unto Your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by what means <hi>Atheiſm, Errors, Evil Examples,</hi> and other Vices, are now grown to this moſt prodigious height: But the Remedy of all theſe things, I muſt leave to the great power of the Almighty God, and to the great Underſtanding, and Care, of Your moſt Gratious Majeſty, and the Honourable Parliament.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:34674:60"/>
               <p>And now again, before I conclude, I cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe but ſay, that I am apt to believe, that their will not be wanting ſome Men, that will be ready enough to cavil with me, or at leaſt, rail upon me, for my undertaking this Work. and perhaps, they may ſay, <hi>For what Reaſon doth ſuch a one as he take upon him to Diſcourſe about Matters of Religion, and State-Affairs? For he himſelf confeſſeth, in his Epiſtle to the Reader, that his Education, was but mean, and Scholar he is none, farther than the</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Tongue; and therefore, how dare ſuch a one as he, take upon himſelf, to ſpeak, or preach at this rate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe ſuppoſitive Objections, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Anſwer.</p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> of all I ſay, That in this Work of mine, I have done nothing at all, that hath in it, in the leaſt, that I know of, any thing of the nature of a daring Faculty; for with all humble ſubmiſſion, (both) with my Heart and Tongue, I have endeavoured (always) ſo much as in me lieth, ſo to ſpeak, as not to offend (any) in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places of Authority, or any other honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Man or Men whatſoever. And as to State-Affairs, I have not at all concerned my ſelf with it, any farther, than to give in unto Your Great Powers, a true Information againſt Frauds, Cheats, Oppreſſion, &amp; Vices. And now, I ſay (God) who is the ſearcher of all Hearts, doth know, that in and by the ſetting forth of this whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in both parts, I aim, at nothing more than the glory of God, the honour and ſafety of the King, and the good and welfare of all good Subjects. And according to the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> his ſaying, in his 16th Chapter of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34674:60"/>verſ. 19. To the beſt of my Capacity I can truly ſay, that in the doing of this, I have only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be wiſe concerning what is good, and I am ſimple in any thing that is or can be evil in the doing of it.</p>
               <p>And therefore, I hope all Men whatſoever, will have ſo much Charity for me, as to believe me, (in what I here ſay;) for the God of Heaven doth know that I ſpeak the truth.</p>
               <p>And now, <hi>2dly,</hi> I ſay, as to Preaching, this Treatiſe of mine, (I think) hath not in it, in the leaſt, any thing of that nature, that may any way (properly) be called Preaching; for I dare not, take upon me, to mention any particular Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (only) to raiſe other Diſcourſes from them, (nor) do I take on me, to raiſe from them Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, (or) Obſervations, (but) I (only) uſe them as (ſupports) to ſtrengthen theſe my ſeveral Arguments; and that (only) on ſuch ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions (as their is) as I think) extraordinary oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for it; and that (only) to ſtir up the Hearts of men, to do what is good, for I think with my ſelf (this,) that tho' ſome men, may not believe theſe my Arguments alone (yet) my hope is, that when my Arguments, are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with God's Word, that then, Men may the ſooner embrace them, and believe in them, But as for Preaching, I dare not think my ſelf, any way qualified, ſo to do; yet nevertheleſs, I think, that this my Treatiſe, may modeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the Name, or Title, of a Friendly Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; and for ſuch a thing as that, with all humble ſubmiſſion, to better Judgments, I preſume ſo to offer it: And in ſo doing, I hope I have not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34674:61"/>done any way amiſs in it, for it is our Imcumbent Duty, every one of us, to adviſe and admoniſh one another, and in ſo doing, we ought to do it, in Word and Deed, with all our Hearts, in the name, of the Lord Jeſus, without reſpect of Perſons, as we may read it, in the 3d. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſions,</hi> the 16, 17, 23, 24, and 25. Verſes. And alſo to the ſame purpoſe, you may read it in the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonins,</hi> the third Chap. the 13, 14, and 15 Verſes.</p>
               <p>And now, I moſt humbly Beſeech, the Great God of Heaven, to beſtow his Bleſſings, upon theſe my weak Endeavours, and alſo, to give you all a Right underſtanding, of this my Poor, Mean, yet, well intended Treatis (now offered unto Your Greatneſes) with an Heart full of Integrity, and true Loyalty, both towards God, the Proteſtant Religion, my King, and Country.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>I am Your Majeſty's Loyal Subject, and the Honourable Parliament's devoted Servant <hi>Richard Newnam</hi> of <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34674:61"/>
               <head>And now at Laſt,</head>
               <head type="sub">With all Humble Submiſſion, and true Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, I here preſent unto Your Moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Majeſty, and the Parliament, the Abſtract of my whole Treatiſe, which I have endeavoured to ſet forth in theſe plain, low ſtile, following Verſes, whoſe Sound, to the moſt Learned, and Eloquent, (muſt needs) be very uncouth, (yet) are in their own ſimple Nature, truly Cordial: And if but rightly applyed, as they are by me (In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently) offered then I ſhall gain my deſired end, in hopes of which, I farther ſay,</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WE have, of late, found (Nature) out of frame,</l>
                  <l>The Stars, lookt Blunt, the Sun ſhin'd not the ſame,</l>
                  <l>To warm the Earth, as did, ſome Years ago;</l>
                  <l>Summer from Winter, we did (hardly) know,</l>
                  <l>But by green Leaves, (which) did to us appear,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew, the Revolution, of the Year;</l>
                  <l>But Graſs, Herbs, Fruits, came ſcant in their due Seaſon.</l>
                  <l>What Star-gazar, (can) give for this, a Reaſon?</l>
                  <l>'Twas, from diſorder, of the (Heavenly) Bodies.</l>
                  <l>But how, or why, paſt knowledge, of ſuch Nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34674:62"/>
                  <l>As took on them, (ſuch) Secrets to diſcover;</l>
                  <l>They fail'd, in that, as they (do) in the Weather.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Gadbury,</hi> in the late, <hi>James</hi>'s his Reign,</l>
                  <l>To him, predicted Conqueſt, all in vain,</l>
                  <l>And ſo <hi>Partridge,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King quite cry'd down,</l>
                  <l>And meant, as if he needs, muſt loſe his Crown:</l>
                  <l>Which, if he had, then <hi>England,</hi> might Rejoyce.</l>
                  <l>But more ile ſay, now, with a chearful Voice,</l>
                  <l>God grant, our King, by God protected be,</l>
                  <l>Not fear, nor truſt, doubtful, <hi>Aſtrologie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now again, to my, intended Theme,</l>
                  <l>We yet may feel, what God, by this doth mean</l>
                  <l>Mens wickedneſs, God's Bleſſings, do withſtand,</l>
                  <l>And bring, ſore Evil's, on a fruitful Land.<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Read the 5th Chap. of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> more particularly the 25th verſ.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>O <hi>England,</hi> leave, thy Swearing, Curſing, Damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy monſtrous Pride, thy Drunkenneſs, and thy Whoring,<note n="(c)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. Chap. 9.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy Cheating, Thieving, Filching, and Falſe Coining,</l>
                  <l>Thy Undermining, Falſhood, and Purloining,<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 5.12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doſt thou not Fawn, Flatter, Lye, Bribe, and Juggle:</l>
                  <l>Such, Evil Deeds, may bring, on thee, much trouble:<note n="(e)" place="bottom">Read <hi>Amos</hi> 8. the whole chapter.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Stop now in time, God's Eye looks on thy ſcore<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 9.8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. Chap. 12.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>When it is full, he'll viſit thee therefore<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.29.</note>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:34674:62"/>
                  <l>More Dearth, great Want, more Troubls, not leſs one jot,</l>
                  <l>May fall on thee, if thou Repent thee not.<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 4. the whole chapter.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be thou now wiſe, to play, the ſureſt Game,</l>
                  <l>Serve God in Heart, and not only in Name:<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be Faithful, Juſt, Upright, in every thing,<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Amos</hi> 5.24.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Give the poor Subject, right, ſo give the King;</l>
                  <l>Give God his due, the like, give unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 20.25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take thy own due, do right, unto thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,<note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Luke</hi> 6.31. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.27, 28. <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. Chap 22, 23.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fear thou God, honour the King, wiſh all men health,</l>
                  <l>Relieve the Poor, love thy Neighbour, as thy ſelf,<note n="(n)" place="bottom">1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2. Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men rule on Earth, but God, doth rule in Heaven,</l>
                  <l>Expecting Men, to act, both plain, and even.<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. the whole chapter.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>AND now, may't pleaſe, Your Gracious Majeſty;</l>
                  <l>My Muſe, prompts me, to ſing another alay:</l>
                  <l>For with my Soul, (in love) I write to You,</l>
                  <l>And now, will ſay no more, than I think True.<note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.25.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>If You have Foes (whoſe) hatred, You may dread,</l>
                  <l>Its now high time, poor Subjects, to regard:</l>
                  <l>In your defence, by Foes, they'l (not) be Branded,</l>
                  <l>If Poverty, don't make them, too weak-handed:</l>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:34674:63"/>
                  <l>But pinching, pineing, ſtarving, Miſery,<note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov</hi> 14. Chap. 18. and 28.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hereafter (may) drive, ſome, from Loyalty.</l>
                  <l>Some Men there be, that have, abus'd Your Truſt,</l>
                  <l>Which makes the Poor, within them take diſguſt.</l>
                  <l>Your Laws are juſt, Your (Taxes) juſt, but then</l>
                  <l>Unjuſtly laid, on ſome, by Unjuſt Men.<note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>The God of Heaven, Juſtice, doth command,</l>
                  <l>And, ſo do You, that now, do rule our Land:<note n="(s)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ah</hi> 6.8.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But Men pervert it, for to ſerve their Will,</l>
                  <l>Their own baſe Luſt, (and) Hearts deſire fulfil.<note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.26.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis now, high time, the upright, Scale to ſway,</l>
                  <l>Which tottering hangs, (and) Breaking every way.<note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.28.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Grand Sir, I've ſaid, what I think, to be true,</l>
                  <l>Much more would ſay, that may prove good to You,</l>
                  <l>If that I might, But, once, permitted be,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak the Truth, before, Your Majeſty.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From my Houſe at</hi> Tiverton <hi>in</hi> Devonſhire, <date>June <hi>the</hi> 6th, 1698.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="addendum">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:34674:63"/>
               <head>And Laſt of all,</head>
               <head type="sub">For the good of this Great, and Honourable City of <hi>London,</hi> as well as for the Country, I cannot otherwiſe but offer unto Your Moſt Gratious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's, and the Parliament's, Conſideration, this one thing more.</head>
               <p>DUring the whole time, of my now being in <hi>London,</hi> I have always taken my Victuals, from the Cooks, as many other Lodgers, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, and Strangers, daily do the like. And thus, when People from all Places, both from City and Country, reſort to ſuch Houſes, they are apt to complain, and tell, how extreamly Dear they pay for every thing: And ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, as theſe, many times, from the Mouths of all ſorts of People, I have oftentimes heard: And many of thoſe People, who are altogether Strangers to me, have ſaid in my hearing, <hi>That if it were not, for ſome greedy-minded Men, that do make a continual Trade of it, to foreſtall Markets, [Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions] would not have been (altogether) ſo dear here in</hi> London, <hi>as of late they have been, and now at preſent are.</hi> And it is now a common thing, for Country Graſiers, to take up their abode here in the City of <hi>London;</hi> and when they know of any Cattle that is coming up to this City, and that the Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or Owners thereof, are not ſo well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Prices of Cattel, what they will yield here in <hi>London</hi>-Markets. [Then] thoſe Graſiers, which take up their abode here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> only to make advantage of all ſuch Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, when they know of the coming up of ſuch Cattle, then they meet them in their way,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34674:64"/>upon the Road, (perhaps) thirty, or forty Miles from <hi>London;</hi> and ſo buy up ſuch Cattle there upon the Road; and after that, drive them to <hi>London,</hi> [and then] fell them much dearer, than the firſt Owners of them would have ſold them, if they had drove them into <hi>London</hi> themſelves: And the like Fore-ſtalling, or Engroſſing Trade, is alſo continually uſed, in buying up before-hand all other ſorts of Proviſions whatſoever, here in <hi>London:</hi> And in all <hi>England</hi> over, it is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a common Trade, ſo that 'tis thought that there are [now] in <hi>England</hi> more Engroſſers, Huckſters, and Regrators, than of any other (one) Trade whatſoever. And in fine, to ſay all, in a word or too, ſuch Doings, as theſe, are now become the very Bane of <hi>England;</hi> for it will always create a continual Dearth on all ſorts of Proviſions: And what is this otherwiſe, (than) a taking away the Staff of Bread, and the Stay of Proviſions, from the Poor and Needy; [or] do not ſuch things as theſe, (prove) to many poor People, (at laſt) a meer lingering Death it ſelf; for it is they poor Creatures, that at laſt, pay for all. For they have neither their due Weight nor Meaſure, in any thing that they buy, from ſuch Huckſtring Regrators. And all ſuch Engroſſing Trades, are of no better uſe to <hi>England,</hi> than to make fat, and puff up in Pride, a meer Bruitiſh, Heatheniſh, and Swiniſh ſort of People, to the meer deſtruction, or almoſt ſtarving of many honeſt, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and temperate <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who have in them ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Minds, and tender Conſciences, and brave ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Spirits: And ſuch Men as theſe, cannot take Liberty of Conſcience to ſhark, in thoſe hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tims, as other Irreligious and Ungodly Cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34674:64"/>will always do; and therefore it is, that (now) in thoſe days, honeſt poor Men, are moſt of all driven to the Wall with Poverty; and the days are now come, wherein an Honeſt Man can hardly live. And all thoſe things are (only) through Mens want of the Grace of God, and want of Chriſtian Charity to one another; for their is ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enough in our Land, of all things, only Men (will) to gratifie their own baſe Pride, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Over-reach, Cheat, Coufen, and Starve one another. And after all this, can we think that God will not viſit us for theſe things? Or can we, both by Reaſon, or Scripture, expect any farther Bleſſings from the Hands of God, ſo long as we continue to live in theſe known Evil Ways. (Oh) let us have a care, for tho Sentence againſt Evil-doers, is not ſpeedily exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, yet at laſt, it will ſurely be done upon us, unleſs in the mean time, we repent, and forſake our Evil Ways: See what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith in his 8th Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12, &amp; 13 verſes. And theſe things alſo, with all humble Submiſſion, I leave to the Conſideration of Your moſt Gracious Majeſty, and the moſt Honourable Parliament.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I rest in true Love, with all Humble Obedience, Your Majeſty's Loyal Subject, and the moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Parliament's devoted Servant,</hi> Richard Newnam.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:65"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Readers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN looking over this Treatiſe, I have obſerved ſome Letteral Faults, which will not much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sence of theſe Diſcourſes, if the Courteous Readers will but be pleas'd to favour theſe Lines, and uſe (rightly) their own unbyaſed Reaſons, in their peruſal of them: But however, for the better ſatisfaction of all People, I have printed this <hi>Errata,</hi> by which, with a little Care and Pains, you may be ſatisfied in any of the Faults, which you may diſcover in the whole work.</p>
            <p>PAge 3. line 26. for <hi>onlv</hi> read <hi>only.</hi> pag. 9. in ſeveral placees for <hi>crack'd,</hi> read <hi>crackt.</hi> pag. 36. line 32. read <hi>buy their Corn.</hi> pag. 41. line 4. for <hi>it</hi> read <hi>if.</hi> pag. 42. line 20. for <hi>tme</hi> read <hi>time.</hi> pag. 52. line 8. for <hi>uphoden</hi> read <hi>upholden.</hi> pag. 49. with the Letter [I] at the bottom of the ſame Leaf, ſhould be marked in the Folio 57, and ſo onwards accordingly; but this miſtake is not worth your obſervation, becauſe notwithſtanding that, yet the Diſcourſe of the whole Treatiſe leads on in its due and orderly method pag. 59. line 11. for <hi>Geneſis</hi> 24 chap. 15 verſ. read 42 chap. 15 verſ. pag. 61. line 5. look <hi>Geneſis</hi> 7 chap. verſ. 12. and ſo read onward to the end of the Chapter. pag. 75. line 27. read <hi>I am apt.</hi> pag. 84. line 26. <hi>for timet he, read the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34674:65"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
